<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
	 <author email="bburns@apache.org">Michael Stover, brendan Burns, et al.</author>
	 <title>Using JMeter</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="JMeter over RMI">
<p>
In most real world web application environments the machine running the web
application is not the machine which is sitting on your desk.  However to
get a true estimate of performance you would like to be measuring the
true response time of your server, not any (highly variable) network
bottle-necks that might exist between you and the machine on which your web
application is running.  At the same time using a GUI especially a Java
GUI over the network is at best painful (using Un*x and X) and at times not
possible (using windows).
</p>
<p>
To solve this problem JMeter provides a client-server architecture for load
and performance testing which allows the JMeterEngine (the tester) to
reside and run on your application server while the configuration GUI and
visualization executes on the development machine.  This offers a number
of features:
<ul>
	<li>True performance measurment without network bottlenecks</li>
	<li>Fast responsive GUI</li>
	<li>Saving of test samples to a local machine</li>
	<li>Managment of multiple JMeterEngines from a single machine</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>
<section name="Running the JMeter engine on the server">
<p>
Follow the <a href="installing.html">instructions</a> for installing
JMeter.  Once JMeter is sucessfully installed you will need to put the
<code>.../JMeter1.6/bin/ApacheJMeter.jar</code> into your
<code>CLASSPATH</code> environment variable and execute
<code>rmiregistry</code>.  Once the RMI registry is started you will need
to start the actual JMeterServer.  To do this run the
<code>jmeter-server</code> (Un*x) or <code>jmeter-server.bat</code>
script (windows) to start the server.  Your server should now be started,
to test it follow the instructions for running the JMeter client.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Running the JMeter client">
<p>
Once JMeter is sucessfully installed you need to modify the
<code>jmeter.properties</code> file in the bin directory.  Change the
<code>remote_hosts</code> property to include the address of your server.
Next run <code>jmeter</code> (Un*x) or
<code>jmeter.bat</code> (windows) to connect to the JMeter Engine.
If everything works as planned you will be connected with the JMeter
Engine and JMeter will behave exactly as if you were running it all
locally.  See the <a href="user_manual/index.html">user manual</a> for
detailed instructions.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>