<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
	 <author email="bburns@apache.org">Michael Stover, brendan Burns, et al.</author>
	 <title>Visualizers</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="Visualizers">
<p>
Visualizers process sample data during a test run - usually for the purpose of
displaying the data visually.  Adding a visualizer to your threadgroup is as
simple as right-clicking on the threadgroup, and choosing the visualizer you want to
add.  Here is a rundown of some of the more popular visualizers.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Graphing Visualizer">
<p>The simplest and most straightforward, the graphing visualizer simply plots the
data points on a graph.  Each black dot represents a sample, its vertical height
represents time in milliseconds that it took that sample to return.  Average (blue)
and standard deviation (red) are also plotted on the same graph, also in
milliseconds.
</p>
</section>
<section name="View Results Visualizer">
<p>This visualizer allows the user to view the text returned from the sample.
The usefulness of this visualizer depends on what you are testing.  If you are testing
web pages, you will be able to examine the HTML from each sample.  You can hit
the "Next" button repeatedly to view each subsequent sample.  Please note that while
you examine the samples, sampling continues, and all results are stored in memory,
so you may want to stop the test after a few cycles and then examine the results.
I typically use this visualizer initially to verify everything is going smoothly,
and then I remove it and up the thread count for the real test.
</p>
</section>
<section name="File Reporter">
<p>Sometimes also called the File Visualizer, this visualizer returns no visual data,
but rather stores the data to file.  This file can later be viewed by choosing
from the menu (Report->Analyze Data File), and browsing to the generated file.  The
data stored is very simple - URL and time in milliseconds.
</p>
<p>To use the File reporter effectively, be sure to Open the file before starting the
test, and Close the file after you stop the test.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Spline Visualizer">
<p>The spline visualizer presents a smooth curve that represents the data from the
entire test run.  There are 10 points on the curve, each point represents an average
of some subset of the sample run.  For instance, if your test run has been running
for some time, and you have 1000 samples, the first "point" on the curve will represent
an average of the first 100 samples, the next will be for the second 100 samples, etc.
These points are connected using spline curves, and allow users to see the entire
history of the test and how the responsiveness of their application has changed over
time.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>