<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: Assertions</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="4.5 Assertions">
<p><b>WORK IN PROGRESS</b></p>

<p>Assertions allow you to assert facts about responses received from the 
server being tested. Using an assertion, you can essentially "test" that your 
application is returning the results you expect it to. </p>

<p>For instance, you can assert that the response to a query will contain some 
particular text. The text you specify can be a Perl-style regular expression, and 
you can indicate that the response is to contain the text, or that it should match 
the whole response.</p>

<p>You can add an assertion to any Generative Controller. For example, you can 
add an assertion to a HTTP Request that checks for the text, "&lt;/HTML&gt;".  JMeter 
will then check that the text is present in the HTTP response.  If JMeter cannot find the 
text, then it will mark this as a failed request.</p>

<p>To view the assertion results, add an Assertion Listener to the Thread Group.</p>

<p><b>Control Panel</b></p>
<p><img src="../images/screenshots/assertion/assertion.gif" width="446" height="296"></img>
<br>Figure 1 - Assertion Control Panel</br></p>
<p>Properties:
<ul>
  <li>Name - Descriptive name for this element that is shown in the tree. </li>
  <li><i>Response Field to Test</i></li>
  <ul>
    <li>Text Response - </li>
    <li>URL Sampled - </li>
  </ul>
  <li><i>Pattern Matching Rules</i></li>
  <ul>
    <li>Contains - </li>
    <li>Matches - </li>
    <li>Not - </li>
  </ul>
  <li><i>Patterns to Test</i></li>
  <ul>
    <li>(Text Area) - </li>
    <li>Add Button - </li>
    <li>Clear Button - </li>
  </ul>
</ul>
</p>

<p><b>Example</b></p>

<p><img src="../images/screenshots/assertion/example1a.gif" width="190" height="170"></img>
<br>Figure 2 - Test Plan</br></p>

<p><img src="../images/screenshots/assertion/example1b.gif" width="489" height="298"></img>
<br>Figure 3 - Assertion Control Panel with Pattern</br></p>

<p><img src="../images/screenshots/assertion/example1c-pass.gif" width="474" height="265"></img>
<br>Figure 4 - Assertion Listener Results (Pass)</br></p>

<p><img src="../images/screenshots/assertion/example1c-fail.gif" width="474" height="265"></img>
<br>Figure 5 - Assertion Listener Results (Fail)</br></p>

<p>The assertion control panel let's you add strings to be tested. These strings can 
be regular expressions. You can also choose whether the strings will be expected 
to match the entire response, or if the response is only expected to contain the 
strings. You can attach multiple assertions to any controller for additionaly flexibility.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
