<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   $Header$
   Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation
 
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document prev="intro.html" next="build-test-plan.html" date="$Date$">

<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: Getting Started</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="2. Getting Started" anchor="get_started">
<p>The easiest way to begin using JMeter is to first
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/downloads/index.html">download the latest production release</a> and install it.
The release contains all of the files you need to build and run Web, FTP, JDBC, and JNDI tests.</p>
<p>If you want to perform JDBC testing,
then you will, of course, need the appropriate JDBC driver from your vendor.  JMeter does not come with
any JDBC drivers.</p>
<p>
Other software that you may want to download:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.beanshell.org/">BeanShell</a></li>
<li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/glasgow/jaf.html">Java Activation Framework</a> - needed for JavaMail</li>
<li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/index.jsp">Java Mail</a> - needed for mail visualiser and SOAP tests</li>
<li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jms/docs.html">JMS</a> - for JMS samplers</li>
<li><a href="http://java.sun.com/downloads/">General Java download page</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
<note>
Any additional jars need to be stored in the JMeter lib directory (or the appropriate JRE directory). 
Make sure the file extension is .jar, not .zip, as JMeter only looks for .jar files.
</note>
<p>Next, start JMeter and go through the <a href="build-test-plan.html">Building a Test Plan</a> section
of the User Guide to familiarize yourself with JMeter basics (for example, adding and removing elements).</p>
<p>Finally, go through the appropriate section on how to build a specific type of Test Plan.
For example, if you are interested in testing a Web application, then see the section
<a href="build-web-test-plan.html">Building a Web Test Plan</a>.
The other specific Test Plan sections are for <a href="build-db-test-plan.html">JDBC</a>,
<a href="build-ftp-test-plan.html">FTP</a>, and <a href="build-jndi-test-plan.html">JNDI</a>.</p>
<p>Once you are comfortable with building and running JMeter Test Plans, you can look into the
various configuration elements (timers, listeners, assertions, and others) which give you more control
over your Test Plans.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.1 Requirements" anchor="requirements">
<p>JMeter requires your computing environment meets some minimum requirements.</p>

<subsection name="2.1.1 Java Version" anchor="java_versions">
<p>JMeter requires a fully compliant JVM 1.3 or higher.  
We are making a strong effort currently to be compatible with the 1.3 JVM's, though it is expected JMeter performs best with 1.4 or better. 
</p>
<p>Because JMeter uses only standard Java APIs, please do not file bug reports if your JRE fails to run
JMeter because of JRE implementation issues.</p>
<note>
Java 1.3 does not include SSL (HTTPS) support - you'll need to download JSSE.
Also, it does not perform as well as later Java versions. 
Use the latest version of Java 1.4 or 1.5 for best results
</note>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.1.2 Operating Systems" anchor="os">
<p>JMeter is a 100% Java application and should run correctly on any system
that has a compliant Java implementation.<br/>
JMeter has been tested and works under:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Unix (Solaris, Linux, etc)</li>
<li>Windows (98, NT, 2000, XP)</li>
<li>OpenVMS Alpha 7.3+</li>
</ul>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="2.2 Optional" anchor="optional">
<p>If you plan on doing JMeter development or want to use Sun's Java Standard Extension packages, then you will need one or more optional packages listed below.</p>


<subsection name="2.2.1 Java Compiler" anchor="opt_compiler">
<p>If you want to build the JMeter source or develop JMeter plugins, then you will need a fully compliant JDK 1.3 or higher.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.2.2 SAX XML Parser" anchor="opt_sax">
<p>JMeter comes with Apache's <a href="http://xml.apache.org/">Xerces XML parser</a>. You have the option of telling JMeter
to use a different XML parser. To do so, include the classes for the third-party parser in JMeter's <a href="#classpath">classpath</a>,
and update the <a href="#configuring_jmeter">jmeter.properties</a> file with the full classname of the parser
implementation.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.2.3 Email Support" anchor="opt_email">
<p>JMeter has limited Email capabilities. It can send email based on test results, and has a POP/IMAP sampler.
It does not currently support SMTP sampling.
To enable Email support, add Sun's JavaMail packages and the activation packages to JMeter's <a href="#classpath">classpath</a>.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.2.4 SSL Encryption" anchor="opt_ssl">
<p>To test a web server using SSL encryption (HTTPS), JMeter requires that an
implementation of SSL be provided (such as Sun's <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/index.html">Java Secure Sockets Extension -- JSSE</a>).
Include the necessary encryption packages in JMeter's <a href="#classpath">classpath</a>.  Also, update <a href="#configuring_jmeter">jmeter.properties</a>
by registering the SSL Provider.</p>
<p>There is also the <complink name="SSL Manager"/>, for greater control of certificates.</p>
<p>Note: if you are running JDK1.4, then you do not have to download JSSE because Sun integrated it into JDK1.4 as a standard library.</p>
<p>The JMeter proxy server (see below) does not support recording SSL (https).</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.2.5 JDBC Driver" anchor="opt_jdbc">
<p>You will need to add your database vendor's JDBC driver to the <a href="#classpath">classpath</a> if you want to do JDBC testing.
Make sure the file is a jar file, not a zip.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.2.6 Apache SOAP" anchor="opt_soap">
<p>Apache SOAP requires mail.jar and activation.jar. You need to download and copy these two jar files to your jmeter/lib directory. Once the files are in there, JMeter will automatically pick them up.</p>
</subsection>
<note>
Any additional jars need to be stored in the JMeter lib directory (or the appropriate JRE directory). 
Make sure the file extension is .jar, not .zip, as JMeter only looks for .jar files.
</note>
</section>

<section name="2.3 Installation" anchor="install">
<p>Installing JMeter is a snap.  Specifics depend on which release file you
downloaded.</p>

<p><b>Note: avoid installing JMeter in a path with spaces in the name.  
This causes problems for remote testing.</b></p>
<subsection name="2.3.1 Downloading the Latest Release" anchor="download_release">
<p>We recommend that most users run the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/downloads/index.html">latest release</a>.</p>
<p>To install a release build, simply unzip the zip/tar file into the directory
where you want JMeter to be installed.  Provided that you have a JRE/JDK correctly installed
and the JAVA_HOME environment variable set, there is nothing more for you to do.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.3.2 Downloading Nightly Builds" anchor="download_nightly">
<p>If you do not mind working with beta-quality software, then you can download and run the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-jmeter/nightly">latest nightly build</a>.</p>
<p>To install a nightly build, unzip the _bin and _lib zip/tar files into the same directory structure.
Provided that you have a JRE/JDK correctly installed
and the JAVA_HOME environment variable set, JMeter should be installed successfully.</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="2.4 Running JMeter" anchor="running">
<br/>
<p>To run JMeter, run the jmeter.bat (for Windows) or jmeter (for Unix) file. 
JMeter must be started from the JMeter bin directory (where those files are found).
The jmeter.bat file attempts to change to the appropriate directory if it can.
</p>

<subsection name="2.4.1 JMeter's Classpath" anchor="classpath">
<p>JMeter automatically finds classes from jars in its /lib and /lib/ext directories.  
If you have developed new JMeter components,
then you should jar them and copy the jar into JMeter's /lib/ext directory.  JMeter will
automatically find JMeter components in any jars found here. 
Other jars (such as JDBC, and any support libaries needed by the JMeter code)
 should be placed in the lib directory.</p>
<p>Note: JMeter will only find .jar files, not .zip.</p>
<p>You can also install utility Jar files in $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/ext, or (since 2.1.1) you can set the property user.classpath in jmeter.properties</p>
<p>Note that setting the CLASSPATH environment variable will have no effect.
This is because JMeter is started with "java -jar", 
and the java command silently ignores the CLASSPATH variable, and the -classpath/-cp options when -jar is used. 
[This occurs with all Java programs, not just JMeter.]</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.4.2 Using a Proxy Server" anchor="proxy_server">
<p>If you are testing from behind a firewall/proxy server, you may need to provide JMeter with
the firewall/proxy server hostname and port number.  To do so, run the jmeter.bat/jmeter file
from a command line with the following parameters:</p>
<p>-H [proxy server hostname or ip address]<br/>
-P [proxy server port]<br/>
-u [username for proxy authentication - if required]<br/>
-a [password for proxy authentication - if required]</p>
<p><b>Example</b>: jmeter -H my.proxy.server -P 8000 -u username -a password</p>
<p>Alternatively, you can use --proxyHost, --proxyPort, --username, and --password</p>
<note>JMeter also has its own in-built <complink name="HTTP Proxy Server">HTTP Proxy Server</complink>,
which can be used for recording HTTP (but not HTTPS) browser sessions.
This is not to be confused with the proxy settings described above, which are used when JMeter makes HTTP or HTTPS requests itself.</note>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.4.3 Non-GUI Mode (Command Line mode)" anchor="non_gui">
<p>For non-interactive testing, you may choose to run JMeter without the GUI. To do so, use
the following command options</p>
<p>-n This specifies JMeter is to run in non-gui mode</p>
<p>-t [name of JMX file that contains the Test Plan].</p>
<p>-l [name of JTL file to log sample results to].</p>
<p>-r Run all remote servers specified in jmeter.properties (or remote servers specified on command line by overriding properties)</p>
<p>The script also lets you specify the optional firewall/proxy server information:</p>
<p>-H [proxy server hostname or ip address]<br/>
-P [proxy server port]</p>
<p><b>Example</b>: jmeter -n -t my_test.jmx -l log.jtl -H my.proxy.server -P 8000</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.4.4 Server Mode" anchor="server">
<p>For <a href="remote-test.html">distributed testing</a>, run JMeter in server mode, and then control each server from the GUI.
<note>The jmeter-server/jmeter-server.bat script should start rmiregistry for you with the appropriate classpath.  if it fails to
do so, <a href="remote-test.html#detail_instructions">read the details</a> about starting the jmeter server.</note>

Run jmeter-server/jmeter-server.bat, plus these optional commands:</p>
<p>The script also lets you specify the optional firewall/proxy server information:</p>
<p>-H [proxy server hostname or ip address]<br/>
-P [proxy server port]</p>
<p><b>Example</b>: jmeter-server -H my.proxy.server -P 8000</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="2.4.5 Overriding Properties Via The Command Line" anchor="override">
<p>Java system properties, JMeter properties, and logging properties can be overriden directly on the command line (instead of modifying jmeter.properties).
To do so, use the following options:</p>
<p>-D[prop_name]=[value] - defines a java system property value.</p>
<p>-J[prop name]=[value] - overrides a JMeter property.</p>
<p>-L[category]=[priority] - overrides a logging setting, setting a particular category to the given priority level.</p>
<p>The -L flag can also be used without the category name to set the root logging level.</p>
	<p><b>Examples</b>:
<pre>
jmeter -Duser.dir=/home/mstover/jmeter_stuff \
    -Jremote_hosts=127.0.0.1 -Ljmeter.engine=DEBUG

jmeter -LDEBUG</pre>
</p>
<p>
<b>N.B.<br/>
	The command line properties are processed early in startup, but after the logging system has been set up.
	Attempts to use the -J flag to update log_level or log_file properties will have no effect.</b>
	</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="2.4.6 Logging and error messages" anchor="logging">
	<p>If JMeter detects an error, a message will be written to the log file. 
		The log file name is defined in the jmeter.properties file.
		It is normally defined as <b>jmeter.log</b>, and will be found in the JMeter startup directory, i.e. bin.
		</p>
		<p>When running on Windows, the file may appear as just <b>jmeter</b> unless you have set Windows to show file extensions.
		[Which you should do anyway, to make it easier to detect viruses and other nasties that pretend to be text files...]
		</p>
		<p>As well as recording errors, the jmeter.log file records some information about the test run. For example:</p>
<pre>
10/17/2003 12:19:20 PM INFO  - jmeter.JMeter: Version 1.9.20031002 
10/17/2003 12:19:45 PM INFO  - jmeter.gui.action.Load: Loading file: c:\mytestfiles\BSH.jmx 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.engine.StandardJMeterEngine: Running the test! 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.engine.StandardJMeterEngine: Starting 1 threads for group BSH. Ramp up = 1. 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.engine.StandardJMeterEngine: Continue on error 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.threads.JMeterThread: Thread BSH1-1 started 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.threads.JMeterThread: Thread BSH1-1 is done 
10/17/2003 12:19:52 PM INFO  - jmeter.engine.StandardJMeterEngine: Test has ended 	
</pre>
<p>The log file can be helpful in determining the cause of an error,
	as JMeter does not interrupt a test to display an error dialogue.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="2.4.7 Full list of command-line options" anchor="options">
<p>Invoking JMeter as "jmeter -?" will print a list of all the command-line options. 
These are shown below.</p>
<pre>
        -h, --help
                print usage information and exit
        -v, --version
                print the version information and exit
        -p, --propfile {argument}
                the jmeter property file to use
        -q, --addprop {argument}
                additional property file(s)
        -t, --testfile {argument}
                the jmeter test(.jmx) file to run
        -l, --logfile {argument}
                the file to log samples to
        -n, --nongui
                run JMeter in nongui mode
        -s, --server
                run the JMeter server
        -H, --proxyHost {argument}
                Set a proxy server for JMeter to use
        -P, --proxyPort {argument}
                Set proxy server port for JMeter to use
        -u, --username {argument}
                Set username for proxy server that JMeter is to use
        -a, --password {argument}
                Set password for proxy server that JMeter is to use
        -J, --jmeterproperty {argument}={value}
                Define additional JMeter properties
        -D, --systemproperty {argument}={value}
                Define additional JMeter properties
        -L, --loglevel {argument}={value}
                Define loglevel: [category=]level 
                e.g. jorphan=INFO or jmeter.util=DEBUG
        -r, --runremote
                Start remote servers from non-gui mode
        -d, --homedir {argument}
                the jmeter home directory to use
</pre>
</subsection>
</section>


<section name="2.5 Configuring JMeter" anchor="configuring_jmeter">
<p>If you wish to modify the properties with which JMeter runs you need to
  either modify the jmeter.properties inside of the /bin directory or create
  your own copy of the jmeter.properties and specify it in the command line.
  </p>
  <properties>
	<property name="ssl.provider">You can specify the class for your SSL
	implementation.  If you are using the JSSE from sun, then it is:<br/>
	com.sun.net.ssl.internal.ssl.Provider.  JMeter, by default, should provide https support is you are
	using JDK1.4 or if you use JDK1.3 with the JSSE class jars in your JMeter classpath.</property>
	<property name="xml.parser">You can specify an implementation as your XML
	parser.  The default value is: org.apache.xerces.parsers.SAXParser</property>
  <property name="user.dir">The directory JMeter will first go to for saving and
	loading test scripts.</property>
  <property name="remote_hosts">Comma-delimited list of remote JMeter hosts.
	If you are running JMeter in a distributed environment, list the machines where
  you have JMeter remote servers running.  This will allow you to control those
	servers from this machine's GUI</property>
  <property name="not_in_menu">A list of components you do not want to see in
	JMeter's menus.  As JMeter has more and more components added, you may wish to
  customize your JMeter to show only those components you are interested in.
  You may list their classname or their class label (the string that appears
  in JMeter's UI) here, and they will no longer appear in the menus.</property>
  </properties>
<p><b>
See also the comments in the jmeter.properties file for further information on other settings you can change.
</b></p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

