<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: Getting Started</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="2. Getting Started">
<p>The easiest way to begin using JMeter is to first 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-jmeter/release/">download the latest production release</a> and install it. 
The release contains all of the files you need to build and run Web, FTP, JDBC, and JNDI tests.  If you want to perform JDBC testing, 
then you will, of course, need the appropriate JDBC driver from your vendor.  JMeter does not come with
any JDBC drivers.</p>
<p>Next, start JMeter and go through the <a href="build-test-plan.html">Building a Test Plan</a> section 
of the User Guide to familiarize yourself with JMeter basics (for example, adding and removing elements).</p>
<p>Finally, go through the appropriate section on how to build a specific type of Test Plan.
For example, if you are interested in testing a Web application, then see the section 
<a href="build-web-test-plan.html">Building a Web Test Plan</a>.
The other specific Test Plan sections are for <a href="build-db-test-plan.html">JDBC</a>, 
<a href="build-ftp-test-plan.html">FTP</a>, and <a href="build-jndi-test-plan.html">JNDI</a>.</p>
<p>Once you are comfortable with building and running JMeter Test Plans, you can look into the 
various configuration elements (timers, listeners, assertions, and others) which give you more control
over your Test Plans.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.1 Requirements">
<p>As you can see from the list below, JMeter has only one requirement.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.1.1 Java Version">
<p>JMeter requires a fully compliant JDK1.2 (or higher) environment. Because JMeter uses only 
standard Java APIs (java.*), please do not file bug reports if your JRE fails to run 
JMeter because of JRE implementation issues.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2 Optional">
<p>If you plan on doing JMeter development or want to use Sun's Java Standard Extension packages, then you will need one or more optional packages listed below.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.1 Java Compiler">
<p>If you want to build the JMeter source or develop JMeter plugins, then you will need a fully compliant JDK1.2 or higher compiler.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.2 SAX 1.0 XML Parser">
<p>JMeter comes with Apache's <a href="http://xml.apache.org/">Xerces XML parser</a>. You have the option of telling JMeter 
to use a different XML parser.</p> 
</section>

<section name="2.2.3 javax.mail and javax.activation">
<p>You will need these packages if you want JMeter to send email notifications.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.4 Java Secure Socket Extension (JSSE)">
<p>You will need <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/index.html">JSSE</a> if you want JMeter to send HTTPS requests for Web application testing. Note: if you are running JDK1.4, then you do not have to download JSSE because Sun integrated it into JDK1.4 as a standard library.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2 Installation">
<p>Blah, blah, blah.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.1 Downloading the Latest Release">
<p>We recommend that most users run the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-jmeter/release/">latest release</a>.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.2 Downloading Nightly Builds">
<p>If you do not mind working with beta-quality software, then you can download and run the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-jmeter/nightly">latest nightly build</a>.  </p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.3 UNIX Instructions">
<p>Blah, blah, blah.</p>
</section>

<section name="2.2.4 MS-Windows Instructions">
<p>Blah, blah, blah.</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

