<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document[
<!ENTITY sect-num '42'>
<!ENTITY hellip   "&#x02026;" >
]>

<document prev="best-practices.html" next="component_reference.html" id="$Id$">

<properties>
  <author email="dev@jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>
  <title>Include Controller Tutorial</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="&sect-num;. Include Controller Tutorial" anchor="include">
<p>
This is a short tutorial explaining the basics of the Include Controller. The Include Controller
provides an easy way to include modules in a test plan. It is different than the Module Controller
in a couple of ways.
</p>

<ul>
<li>the Include Controller loads a simple controller with all it's samples, where as the Module
    Controller can use any controller</li>
<li>the Include Controller doesn't use the workbench</li>
<li>the Module Controller doesn't load from a file</li>
<li>the Include Controller loads the module at runtime and doesn't display the contents of the
    Simple Controller</li>
</ul>

<p>
There are a couple of reasons why one might want to use the include controller.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Break a test plan into reusable modules</li>
  <li>Reduce the cost of maintaining test plans</li>
  <li>Reduce duplication of common process</li>
</ul>

<p>
For example, say you need to test an application that requires login. If each test plan had the login requests,
a change in the login process would require updating all test plans. By making the login a module, all other
test plans can reuse it. When the login process changes, the change is made to the module and all other test
plans get the change. One limitation of the current implementation is the contents of the module are only
loaded at runtime, so users can't view or edit the contents of an included module.
</p>

<figure width="417" height="130" image="includecontroller.png">Include Controller</figure>

<p>
The Include Controller has two properties. The <code>name</code> and the <code>filename</code>. The <code>name</code>
is the descriptive name for the controller in the test plan. The <code>filename</code> is the name of the <code>.jmx</code> file.
</p>

<subsection name="&sect-num;.1 Step-by-step" anchor="step-by-step">

<ol>
  <li>Start JMeter</li>
  <li>Select the workbench</li>
  <li><menuchoice>
        <guimenuitem>Add</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Logic Controller</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Simple Controller</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
  </li>
  <li>Enter <code>module1</code> in the name</li>
  <li>Now add one or more samples to the controller</li>
  <li>Once the samples are added, right click on <code>module1</code></li>
  <li>Select <code>save as</code> and save it as <code>module1.jmx</code></li>
</ol>

</subsection>

<p>
<code>module1.jmx</code> can now be used with any test plan. The Include Controller hasn't been tested
with other controllers as the root element. If you need to use other controllers, use a Simple Controller
as the root and add other controllers to it.
</p>

</section>

</body>

</document>
