<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

<properties>
  <title>User's Manual: Timers</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="4.4 Timers" anchor="timers">

<p>By default, a JMeter thread sends requests without pausing between each request. 
We recommend that you specify a delay by adding one of the three timers to 
your Thread Group. If you do not add a delay, JMeter could overwhelm your server by 
making too many requests in a very short amount of time.

<ul>
  <li><b>Constant Timer</b> <br></br>Pause each thread request for a particular  
(constant) amount of time.</li> 

  <li><b>Gaussian Random Timer</b> <br></br>Pause each thread request for a random 
amount of time, with most of the time intervals occurring near a particular value.</li> 

  <li><b>Uniform Random Timer</b> <br></br>Pause each thread request for a random 
amount of time, with each time interval having the same probability of occurring.</li> 
</ul>
</p>

<p>
If you choose to add more than one timer to a Thread Group, JMeter takes the sum of 
the timers and pauses for that amount of time.</p>
</section>

<section name="4.4.1 Constant Timer" anchor="constant">
<p>If you want to have each thread pause for the same amount of time between 
requests, use this timer.</p>

<p><img src="../images/screenshots/timers/constant_timer.gif" width="390" height="100" alt="Constant Timer"></img></p>

<p><b>Property Descriptions:</b>
<ul>
  <li><b>Name</b> - Descriptive name for this timer that is shown in the tree. </li>
  <li><b>Thread Delay</b> - Number of milliseconds to pause.</li>
</ul>
</p>


</section>

<section name="4.4.2 Gaussian Random Timer" anchor="gaussian">
<p>This timer pauses each thread request for a random amount of time, with most 
of the time intervals ocurring near a particular value.  The total delay is the 
sum of the Gaussian distributed value (with mean 0.0 and standard deviation 1.0) times
the deviation value you specify, and the offset value.</p>
<p><img src="../images/screenshots/timers/gauss_random_timer.gif" width="390" height="182" alt="Gaussian Random Timer"></img></p>

<p><b>Property Descriptions:</b>
<ul>
  <li><b>Name</b> - Descriptive name for this timer that is shown in the tree. </li>
  <li><b>Deviation</b> - Deviation in milliseconds.</li>
  <li><b>Constant Delay Offset</b> - Numer of milliseconds to pause in addition 
to the random delay.</li>
</ul>
</p>

</section>

<section name="4.4.3 Uniform Random Timer" anchor="uniform">
<p>This timer pauses each thread request for a random amount of time, with 
each time interval having the same probability of occurring. The total delay
is the sum of the random value and the offset value.</p>
<p><img src="../images/screenshots/timers/uniform_random_timer.gif" width="390" height="182" alt="Uniform Random Timer"></img></p>

<p><b>Property Descriptions:</b>
<ul>
  <li><b>Name</b> - Descriptive name for this timer that is shown in the tree. </li>
  <li><b>Random Delay Maximum</b> - Maxium random number of milliseconds to 
pause.</li>
  <li><b>Constant Delay Offset</b> - Numer of milliseconds to pause in addition 
to the random delay.</li>
</ul>
</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>
