<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document
[
<!ENTITY hellip   "&#x02026;" >
<!ENTITY rarr     "&#x02192;" >
<!ENTITY vellip   "&#x022EE;" >
]>
<document>
<properties>
    <author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>
    <title>Changes</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Changes">
<style type="text/css"><!--
h2 { color: #960000; }
h3 { color: #960000; }
--></style>
<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 5.1 =================== -->

<h1>Version 5.1</h1>
<p>
Summary
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#New and Noteworthy">New and Noteworthy</a></li>
<li><a href="#Incompatible changes">Incompatible changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Bug fixes">Bug fixes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Improvements">Improvements</a></li>
<li><a href="#Non-functional changes">Non-functional changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Known problems and workarounds">Known problems and workarounds</a></li>
<li><a href="#Thanks">Thanks</a></li>

</ul>

<ch_section>New and Noteworthy</ch_section>
<ch_title>Core improvements</ch_title>
<p>JDBC testing has been improved with ability to set init SQL statements and add 
compatibility with JDBC drivers that do not support QueryTimeout
<figure width="1122" height="727" image="changes/5.1/jdbc-connection-config-init-request.png" />
</p>
<ul>
<li>Various bug fixes have been implemented, like gathering the correct headers when recording requests through the HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder using HTTPS</li>
<li>In version 5.0, JMeter was changed to rename Sub results using a custom Naming Policy (<bugzilla>62550</bugzilla>). This change could be annoying for Functional Testing, a new property
<code>subresults.disable_renaming=true</code> has been introduced to revert if needed to previous behaviour. An alternative is to check <code>Functional Test Mode</code> in Test Plan, see <bugzilla>63055</bugzilla></li>
</ul>
<ch_title>UX improvements</ch_title>
<p>Templates can provide parameters that are filled in on test plan generation,
<code>Recording</code> template uses this feature
<figure width="726" height="453" image="changes/5.1/templates-parametes.png" />
</p>
<p>A new <code>Tools</code> menu has been introduced to collect those entries,
that are used for general usage around JMeter, like:
<ul>
    <li><code>Function Helper Dialog</code></li>
    <li><code>Export transactions for report</code></li>
    <li><code>Generate Schematic View</code> which provides an overview as HTML of the Test plan</li>
    <li><code>Import from cURL</code> which allows you to create or update your test plan by importing a cURL command</li>
    <li><code>Compile JSR223 Test Elements</code></li>
    <li><code>Create a heap dump</code></li>
    <li><code>Create a thread dump</code></li>
</ul>
<figure width="268" height="237" image="changes/5.1/jmeter-new-menu-tools.png" />
</p>
<ch_title>Test Plan</ch_title>
<p>Ability to create a Test plan from a cURL command.
<figure width="1026" height="439" image="changes/5.1/http-request-from-curl-request.png" />
</p>
<ch_title>Scripting / Debugging enhancements</ch_title>
<ul>
<li>A menu item to compile all JSR223 Elements is now available in <code>Tools</code> menu</li>
</ul>
<ch_title>Live Reporting and Web Report</ch_title>
<ul>
<li>A JSON file containing summary of a load test statistics is now generated when using <code>-e</code> or <code>-g</code> options.</li>
<li>Percentiles computing graphed over time algorithm has been modified to restart for  each time slot</li>
<li>More user-friendly behaviour when reporting folder does not exist or is not empty through <code>-f</code> commmand line option</li>
</ul>
<!--
<ch_title>Functions</ch_title>
-->
<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<ch_section>Incompatible changes</ch_section>
<ul>
<li>In <code>Response Time Percentiles Over Time (successful responses)</code> graph of the HTML report, before this version, percentile computation of each time slot used the percentile data
of previous time slot as a base. Starting with this version, each time slot is independant. See <bugzilla>62883</bugzilla></li>
<li><code>ClientJMeterEngine#rsetProperties</code> signature has been changed to use <code>HashMap&lt;String,String&gt;</code> instead of Properties, see <bugzilla>63034</bugzilla></li>
<li>A new Menu item <code>Tools</code> has been introduced, some menu items that were in <code>Help</code> menu are now under this new menu item. See <bugzilla>63094</bugzilla>
</li>
<li><code>slf4j-ext</code> has been removed from libraries (lib folder) and JMeter pom. It was not used by default and due to CVE-2018-8088 and unavailability of a stable version
containing a fix to this issue, we decided to remove it. If you still needed, you can add it in lib folder.</li>
</ul>
<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<ch_section>Improvements</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62840</bug>HTTP Request: Add option <code>httpclient4.gzip_relax_mode</code> to avoid error when unzipping what seems to be invalid streams</li>
    <li><bug>63025</bug>Enhance Search &amp; Replace functionality for HTTP Request to include port and protocol field. Initial code fix by Mohamed Ibrahim (rollno748 at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62934</bug>Add compatibility for JDBC drivers that do not support QueryTimeout </li>
    <li><bug>62935</bug>Pass custom <code>mail.*</code> properties to Mail Reader Sampler. Implemented by Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com) and contributed by BlazeMeter.</li>
    <li><bug>63055</bug>Don't rename SampleResult Label when test is running in Functional mode or property <code>subresults.disable_renaming=true</code>. Implemented by Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com) and contributed by BlazeMeter.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
  <li><bug>62822</bug><pr>407</pr>Render uninitialized min and max values in Summary Report as <code>#N/A</code></li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62766</bug>Keystore Config: We should load all aliases by default. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62832</bug>JDBC Connection Configuration: Be able to set init SQL statements. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
  <li><bug>63037</bug>When using <code>CSVRead</code> search the script base path for files, too.</li>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Report / Dashboard</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62883</bug>Report / Dashboard: Change the way percentiles are computed for Response Time Percentiles Over Time (successful responses) graph</li>
    <li><bug>63060</bug>Report Generator: A generator should only check for folder/files it generates and only delete those ones</li>
    <li><bug>63059</bug>Create a new JsonExporter that exports as JSON the content of data computed for HTML Dashboard Statistics table. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63081</bug>Command line Option <code>-f</code> does not delete report folder when using generation only through command line option <code>-g</code>. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62959</bug>Ability to create a Test plan from a cURL command. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><pr>394</pr>Allow <code>null</code> values in <code>FieldStringEditor</code>. Based on patch by Mingun (alexander_sergey at mail.ru)</li>
    <li><bug>62826</bug>When changing LAF, make JMeter restart if user clicks yes to popup</li>
    <li><bug>62257</bug><pr>401</pr>Expand/Collapse short key <keysym>-</keysym> (minus sign) on numpad doesn't work. Contributed by Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62752</bug>Add to Documentation: <code>ctx.getThreadNum()</code> is zero-based while <code>${__threadNum}</code> is one-based</li>
    <li><pr>411</pr>Use <code>SHA-1</code> instead of <code>SHA1</code> in <code>org.apache.jmeter.save.SaveService</code>. Contributed by Paco (paco.xu at daocloud.io)</li>
    <li><bug>62914</bug>Add a hint in Thread Group UI about duration of test</li>
    <li><bug>62925</bug>Add support for ThreadDump to the JMeter non-GUI</li>
    <li><bug>62870</bug>Templates: Add ability to provide parameters. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62829</bug>Allow specifying Proxy server scheme for HTTP request sampler, Advanced tab and command line option. Contributed by Hitesh Patel (hitesh.h.patel at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>59633</bug>Menus <code>Save Test Plan as</code>, <code>Save as Test Fragment</code> and <code>Save Selection as ...</code> should use a new file name in File Dialog</li>
    <li><bug>61486</bug>Make jmeter-server and non GUI mode run headless</li>
    <li><bug>63093</bug>Add <code>Compile JSR223 Test Elements</code> menu item. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63094</bug>Introduce a new Tools menu</li>
    <li><bug>63101</bug>Propose a menu item to generate readable overview of Test Plan</li>
    <li><bug>63144</bug>View listener tree take a long time to open response that has huge text. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Non-functional changes</ch_section>
<ul>
    <li><pr>408</pr>Log an informational message instead of an stack trace, when JavaFX is not found for the <code>RenderInBrowser</code> component.</li>
    <li><pr>412</pr>Update Chinese translation. Contributed by 刘士 (liushilive at outlook.com).</li>
    <li><pr>406</pr>Add a short paragraph on how to use a security manager with JMeter.</li>
    <li><bug>62893</bug>Use StringEscapeUtils from commons-text (version 1.6) instead of the deprecated ones from commons-lang3.</li>
    <li><bug>62972</bug><pr>435</pr>Replace calls to deprecated method <code>Class#newInstance</code>.</li>
    <li><bug>63034</bug>ClientJMeterEngine: Make rsetProperties use <code>HashMap&lt;String,String&gt;</code> instead of Properties</li>
    <li>Updated to httpclient/httpmime 4.5.7 (from 4.5.6)</li>
    <li>Updated to httpcore 4.4.11 (from 4.4.10)</li>
    <li>Updated to httpcore-nio 4.4.11 (from 4.4.10)</li>
    <li>Updated to tika-core and tika-parsers 1.20 (from 1.18)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-dbcp2-2.5.0 (from commons-dbcp2-2.4.0)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-lang3-3.8.1 (from commons-lang3-3.8)</li>
    <li>Updated to groovy-all-2.4.16 (from groovy-all-2.4.15)</li>
    <li>Updated to httpasyncclient-4.1.4.jar (from 4.1.3)</li>
    <li>Updated to jsoup-1.11.3 (from 1.11.2)</li>
    <li>Updated to cglib-nodep-3.2.9 (from cglib-nodep-3.2.7)</li>
    <li>Updated to ph-commons-9.2.1 (from ph-commons-9.1.2)</li>
    <li>Updated to log4j-2.11.1 (from log4j-2.11.0)</li>
    <li>Updated to xmlgraphics-commons 2.3 (from 2.2)</li>
    <li><bug>63033</bug>Updated to Saxon-HE 9.9.1-1 (from 9.8.0-12). Thanks at Saxonica</li>
    <li>Updated to xstream 1.4.11 (from 1.4.10)</li>
    <li>Updated to jodd 5.0.6 (from 4.1.4)</li>
    <li>Updated to asm-7.0 (from 6.1)</li>
    <li>Update to ActiveMQ 5.15.8 (from 5.5.16)</li>
    <li>Updated to rsyntaxtextarea-3.0.2 (from 2.6.1)</li>
    <li>Updated to apache-rat-0.13 (from 0.12)</li>
    <li>Updated to jacocoant-0.8.3 (from 0.8.2)</li>
    <li>Updated to hsqldb-2.4.1 (from 2.4.0)</li>
    <li>Updated to mina-core-2.0.19 (from 2.0.16)</li>
    <li><bug>62818</bug>Updated to xercesImpl to 2.12.0 (from 2.11.0). Reported by Stefan Seide (stefan at trilobyte-se.de)</li>
    <li><bug>62744</bug>Upgrade jquery to version 3.3.1, jquery-ui to 1.12.1, bootstrap to 3.3.7</li>
    <li><bug>62821</bug><pr>405</pr>Use SHA-512 checksums instead of MD5 to verify jar downloads</li>
    <li><bug>63053</bug>Remove referrals to never implemented internals from user documentation. Reported by U. Poblotzki (u.poblotzki at thalia.de)</li>
    <li><bug>63082</bug><pr>437</pr>Use utf-8 for properties files in source</li>
    <li><bug>63177</bug>Rename NON GUI mode into CLI Mode in documentation</li>
</ul>

 <!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<ch_section>Bug fixes</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62785</bug><pr>400</pr>Incomplete search path applied to the filenames used in the upload functionality of the HTTP sampler. Implemented by Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com) and contributed by BlazeMeter.</li>
    <li><bug>62842</bug>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder: Brotli compression is not supported leading to "<code>Content Encoding Error</code>"</li>
    <li><bug>60424</bug>Hessian Burlap application: JMeter inserts <code>0x0D</code> before <code>0x0A</code> automatically (http binary post data)</li>
    <li><bug>62940</bug>Use different <code>cn</code> and type of SAN extension when we are generating certificates based on IP addresses.</li>
    <li><bug>62916</bug>HTTP Test Script Recorder fails with UnsupportedOperationException if recording is started after a distributed test has been run</li>
    <li><bug>62987</bug>A TestBean element under HTTP(S) Test Script recorder does not work. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63015</bug>Abnormal NoHttpResponseException when running request through proxy HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder after a first failing request. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62852</bug>HTTP Request Header missing information when using a proxy. Thanks to Oleg Kalnichevski (olegk at apache.org)</li>
    <li><bug>63048</bug>JMeter does not retrieve link resources of type "shortcut icon" or "icon". Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62775</bug>If many jars are in a folder referenced by <code>user.classpath</code>, startup can be extremely slow due to JUnit</li>
    <li><bug>63031</bug>Incorrect JDBC driver class: <code>org.firebirdsql.jdbc.FBDrivery</code>. Contributed by Sonali (arora.sonali99 at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62806</bug>ModuleController cloning by Run behaves differently wether in GUI or Non GUI mode. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62847</bug>If Controller cannot use variable for index exposed by LoopController/WhileController/ForEachController</li>
    <li><bug>63064</bug>Ignore spaces at the end and beginning of expressions used in IfController</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62770</bug>Aggregate Graph throws <code>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</code></li>
    <li><bug>63069</bug>ResultCollector does not write end of XML file if user exits while a Recording or a test is running. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63138</bug>InfluxDB BackendListenerClient: In case of error, log is in debug, it should be in error</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62774</bug>XPath2Extractor: Scope variable is broken. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62860</bug>JSON Extractor: Avoid NPE and noisy error message "<code>Error processing JSON content in</code>" when variable is not found</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Report / Dashboard</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62777</bug>Web Report / Dashboard: Hide All in <code>Response Time Percentiles Over Time (successful responses)</code> fails.</li>
    <li><bug>62780</bug>Web Report / Dashboard: Display All in <code>Response Time Vs Request</code> fails.</li>
    <li><bug>62781</bug>Web Report / Dashboard: Display All in <code>Response Time Overview</code> fails.</li>
    <li><bug>62782</bug>Web Report / Dashboard: Remove duplicate/unused dependencies</li>
    <li><bug>62894</bug>Report / Dashboard: Throughput is in wrong column which is confusing as unit is millisecond</li>
    <li><bug>63016</bug>Empty HTML report if source csv contains labels with quotes. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Documentation</h3>
<ul>
    <li>Change <code>Test Action</code> (old name) to <code>Flow Control Action</code> in Component Reference documentation. Contributed by Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>62745</bug>Fix undefined disabled icon. Contributed by Till Neunast (https://github.com/tilln)</li>
    <li><bug>62743</bug>Client auth must be enabled on distributed testing</li>
    <li><bug>62767</bug>NPE when searching under certain conditions. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62790</bug><code>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</code> when calling replace without selecting the first match</li>
    <li><bug>62795</bug>JMeter master sometimes ends distributed test even though some of the slaves have not finished</li>
    <li><bug>62336</bug><pr>396</pr>Some shortcuts are not working correctly on windows. Contributed by Michael Pavlov (michael.paulau at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62889</bug>Format JSON Arrays when displayed with JSON Path Tester.</li>
    <li><bug>62900</bug>ObjectProperty#getStringValue() can throw NullPointerException</li>
    <li><bug>63099</bug>Escape commata in function helper dialog only outside of variable replacement structures.</li>
    <li><bug>63105</bug>Export Transactions for Report: fix 2 bugs</li>
    <li><bug>63106</bug>Apply naming policy does not refresh UI</li>
    <li><bug>63180</bug>Apply Naming Policy allows multi selection but only considers first node</li>
    <li><bug>63090</bug>Remove slf4j-ext due to CVE-2018-8088</li>
</ul>

 <!--  =================== Thanks =================== -->

<ch_section>Thanks</ch_section>
<p>We thank all contributors mentioned in bug and improvement sections above:
</p>
<ul>
    <li>Oleg Kalnichevski (olegk at apache.org)</li>
    <li>Till Neunast (https://github.com/tilln)</li>
    <li>Mingun (alexander_sergey at mail.ru)</li>
    <li><a href="https://ubikloadpack.com">Ubik Load Pack</a></li>
    <li>Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com)</li>
    <li>Stefan Seide (stefan at trilobyte-se.de)</li>
    <li>刘士 (liushilive at outlook.com)</li>
    <li>Michael Pavlov (michael.paulau at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Paco (paco.xu at daocloud.io)</li>
    <li>Hitesh Patel (hitesh.h.patel at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Sonali (arora.sonali99 at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Mohamed Ibrahim (rollno748 at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>U. Poblotzki (u.poblotzki at thalia.de)</li>
    <li><a href="https://www.saxonica.com">Saxonica</a></li>
</ul>
<p>We also thank bug reporters who helped us improve JMeter.</p>
<ul>
</ul>
<p>
Apologies if we have omitted anyone else.
</p>
 <!--  =================== Known bugs or issues related to JAVA Bugs =================== -->

<ch_section>Known problems and workarounds</ch_section>
<ul>
<li>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</li>

<li>
The numbers that appear to the left of the green box are the number of active threads / total number of threads,
the total number of threads only applies to a locally run test, otherwise it will show <code>0</code> (see <bugzilla>55510</bugzilla>).
</li>

<li>
Note that under some windows systems you may have this WARNING:
<source>
java.util.prefs.WindowsPreferences
WARNING: Could not open/create prefs root node Software\JavaSoft\Prefs at root 0
x80000002. Windows RegCreateKeyEx(&hellip;) returned error code 5.
</source>
The fix is to run JMeter as Administrator, it will create the registry key for you, then you can restart JMeter as a normal user and you won't have the warning anymore.
</li>

<li>
You may encounter the following error:
<source>java.security.cert.CertificateException: Certificates does not conform to algorithm constraints</source>
 if you run a HTTPS request on a web site with a SSL certificate (itself or one of SSL certificates in its chain of trust) with a signature
 algorithm using MD2 (like <code>md2WithRSAEncryption</code>) or with a SSL certificate with a size lower than 1024 bits.
This error is related to increased security in Java 8+.
<br></br>
To allow you to perform your HTTPS request, you can downgrade the security of your Java installation by editing
the Java <code>jdk.certpath.disabledAlgorithms</code> property. Remove the MD2 value or the constraint on size, depending on your case.
<br></br>
This property is in this file:
<source>JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/java.security</source>
See  <bugzilla>56357</bugzilla> for details.
</li>

<li>
Under Mac OSX Aggregate Graph will show wrong values due to mirroring effect on numbers.
This is due to a known Java bug, see Bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8065373" >JDK-8065373</a>
The fix is to use JDK8_u45 or later.
</li>

<li>
View Results Tree may fail to display some HTML code under HTML renderer, see <bugzilla>54586</bugzilla>.
This is due to a known Java bug which fails to parse "<code>px</code>" units in row/col attributes.
See Bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8031109" >JDK-8031109</a>
The fix is to use JDK9 b65 or later.
</li>

<li>
JTable selection with keyboard (<keycombo><keysym>SHIFT</keysym><keysym>up/down</keysym></keycombo>) is totally unusable with Java 7 on Mac OSX.
This is due to a known Java bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8025126" >JDK-8025126</a>
The fix is to use JDK 8 b132 or later.
</li>
</ul>

</section>
</body>
</document>
