<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>   
<properties>     
	<author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>     
	<title>Changes</title>   
</properties> 
<body> 
<section name="Changes"> 

<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 2.7 =================== -->

<h1>Version 2.7</h1>

<h2>New and Noteworthy</h2>


<!--  =================== Known bugs =================== -->

<h2>Known bugs</h2>

<p>
The Include Controller has some problems in non-GUI mode (see Bugs 40671, 41286, 44973, 50898). 
In particular, it can cause a NullPointerException if there are two include controllers with the same name.
</p>

<p>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</p>

<p>Listeners don't show iteration counts when a If Controller has a condition which is always false from the first iteration (see Bug 52496).  
A workaround is to add a sampler at the same level as (or superior to) the If Controller.
For example a Test Action sampler with 0 wait time (which doesn't generate a sample),
or a Debug Sampler with all fields set to False (to reduce the sample size).
</p>

<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<h2>Incompatible changes</h2>

<p>
When doing replacement of User Defined Variables, Proxy will not substitute partial values anymore when "Regexp matching" is used. It will use Perl 5 word matching ("\b")
</p>


<!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<h2>Bug fixes</h2>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Proxy</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 52613 - Using Raw Post Body option, text gets encoded</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 51737 - TCPSampler : Packet gets converted/corrupted</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Assertions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 52551 - Function Helper Dialog does not switch language correctly</li>
<li>Bug 52552 - Help reference only works in English</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 52639 - JSplitPane divider for log panel should be hidden if log is not activated</li>
<li>Bug 52672 - Change Controller action deletes all but one child samplers</li>
<li>Bug 52694 - Deadlock in GUI related to non AWT Threads updating GUI</li>
<li>Bug 52678 - Proxy : When doing replacement of UserDefinedVariables, partial values should not be substituted</li>
<li>Bug 52728 - CSV Data Set Config element cannot coexist with BSF Sampler in same Thread Plan</li>
<li>Bug 52762 - Problem with multiples certificates: first index not used until indexes are restarted</li>
<li>Bug 52741 - TestBeanGUI default values do not work at second time or later</li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<h2>Improvements</h2>

<h3>HTTP Samplers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 52775 - JMS Publisher : Add Non Persistent Delivery option</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 52603 - MailerVisualizer : Enable SSL , TLS and Authentication</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bug 45839 - Test Action : Allow premature exit from a loop</li>
<li>Bug 52614 - MailerModel.sendMail has strange way to calculate debug setting</li>
<li>Bug 52782 - Add a detail button on parameters table to show detail of a Row</li>
</ul>

<h2>Non-functional changes</h2>
<ul>
<li>Upgraded to rhino 1.7R3 (was js-1.7R2.jar). 
Note: the Maven coordinates for the jar were changed from rhino:js to org.mozilla:rhino.
This does not affect JMeter directly, but might cause problems if using JMeter in a Maven project
with other code that depends on an earlier version of the Rhino Javascript jar.
</li>
<li>Bug 52675 - Refactor Proxy and HttpRequestHdr to allow Sampler Creation by Proxy</li>
<li>Bug 52680 - Mention version in which function was introduced</li>
</ul>

</section> 
</body> 
</document>
