<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>   
<properties>     
    <author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>     
    <title>Changes</title>   
</properties> 
<body> 
<section name="Changes"> 
<style type="text/css"><!--
h2 { color: #960000; }
h3 { color: #960000; }
--></style>
<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 2.10 =================== -->

<h1>Version 2.10</h1>

Summary
<ul>
<li><a href="#New and Noteworthy">New and Noteworthy</a></li>
<li><a href="#Known bugs">Known bugs</a></li>
<li><a href="#Incompatible changes">Incompatible changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Bug fixes">Bug fixes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Improvements">Improvements</a></li>
<li><a href="#Non-functional changes">Non-functional changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Thanks">Thanks</a></li>

</ul>

<ch_section>New and Noteworthy</ch_section>

<ch_category>Core Improvements</ch_category>

<ch_title>New Performance improvements</ch_title>
<p>
<ul>
<li>A Huge performance improvement has been made on High Throughput Tests (no pause), see <bugzilla>54777</bugzilla></li>
<li>An issue with unnecessary SSL Context reset has been fixed which improves performances of pure HTTP tests, see <bugzilla>55023</bugzilla></li>
<li>Important performance improvement in parsing of Embedded resource in HTML pages thanks to a switch to JODD/Lagarto HTML Parser, see <bugzilla>55632</bugzilla></li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>New CSS/JQuery Tester in View Tree Results</ch_title>
<p>A new CSS/JQuery Tester in View Tree Results that makes CSS/JQuery Extractor a first class
citizen in JMeter, you can now test your expressions very easily</p>
<p>
<figure width="1144" height="638" image="changes/2.10/01_css_jquery_tester.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Many improvements in HTTP(S) Recording have been made</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="691" height="215" image="changes/2.10/18_https_test_script_recorder.png"></figure>
<note>
The "HTTP Proxy Server" test element has been renamed as "HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder".
</note>
<ul>
<li>Better recording of HTTPS sites, embedded resources using subdomains will more easily be recorded when using JDK 7. See <bugzilla>55507</bugzilla>.
See updated documentation: <complink name="HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder"/>
</li>
<li>Redirection are now more smartly detected by HTTP Proxy Server, see <bugzilla>55531</bugzilla></li>
<li>Many fixes on edge cases with HTTPS have been made, see <bugzilla>55502</bugzilla>, <bugzilla>55504</bugzilla>, <bugzilla>55506</bugzilla></li>
<li>Many encoding fixes have been made, see <bugzilla>54482</bugzilla>, <bugzilla>54142</bugzilla>, <bugzilla>54293</bugzilla></li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>You can now load test MongoDB through new MongoDB Source Config</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="912" height="486" image="changes/2.10/02_mongodb_source_config.png"></figure>
</p>
<p>
<figure width="850" height="687" image="changes/2.10/14_mongodb_jsr223.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Kerberos authentication has been added to Auth Manager</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="1005" height="364" image="changes/2.10/15_kerberos.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Device can now be used in addition to source IP address</ch_title>

<p>
<figure width="1087" height="699" image="changes/2.10/16_device.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>You can now do functional testing of MongoDB scripts through new MongoDB Script</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="906" height="313" image="changes/2.10/03_mongodb_script_alpha.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Timeout has been added to OS Process Sampler</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="684" height="586" image="changes/2.10/17_os_process_timeout.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Query timeout has been added to JDBC Request</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="540" height="600" image="changes/2.10/04_jdbc_request_timeout.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>New functions (__urlencode and __urldecode) are now available to encode/decode URL encoded chars</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="512" height="240" image="changes/2.10/05_urlencode_function.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Continuous Integration is now eased by addition of a new flag that forces NON-GUI JVM to exit after test end</ch_title>
<p>See jmeter property:</p>
<code>jmeterengine.force.system.exit</code>
<p></p>

<ch_title>HttpSampler now allows DELETE Http Method to have a body (works for HC4 and HC31 implementations). This allows for example to test Elastic Search APIs</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="573" height="444" image="changes/2.10/06_http_request_delete_method.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>2 implementations of HtmlParser have been added to improve Embedded resources parsing</ch_title>
<p>
You can choose the implementation to use for parsing Embedded resources in HTML pages:
See jmeter.properties and look at property "htmlParser.className".
<ul>
<li>org.apache.jmeter.protocol.http.parser.LagartoBasedHtmlParser for optimal performances</li>
<li>org.apache.jmeter.protocol.http.parser.JSoupBasedHtmlParser for most accurate parsing and functional testing</li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>Distributed testing has been improved</ch_title>
<p>
<ul>
<li>
Number of threads on each node are now reported to controller.
<p>
<figure width="988" height="355" image="changes/2.10/17_threads_summariser.png"></figure>
</p>
<p>
<figure width="125" height="33" image="changes/2.10/17_threads_gui.png"></figure>
</p>

</li>
<li>Performance improvement on BatchSampleSender(<bugzilla>55423</bugzilla>)</li>
<li>Addition of 2 SampleSender modes (StrippedAsynch and StrippedDiskStore), see jmeter.properties</li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>ModuleController has been improved to better handle changes to referenced controllers</ch_title>

<ch_title>Improved class loader configuration, see <bugzilla>55503</bugzilla></ch_title>
<p>
<ul>
<li>New property "plugin_dependency_paths" for plugin dependencies</li>
<li>Properties "search_paths", "user.classpath" and "plugin_dependency_paths"
    now automatically add all jars from configured directories</li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>Best-practices section has been improved, ensure you read it to get the most out of JMeter</ch_title>
<p>See <a href="usermanual/best-practices.html">Best Practices</a>
</p>
<ch_category>GUI and ergonomy Improvements</ch_category>


<ch_title>New Templates feature that allows you to create test plan from existing template or merge
template into your Test Plan</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="428" height="130" image="changes/2.10/07_jmeter_templates_icon.png"></figure>
</p>
<p>
<figure width="781" height="472" image="changes/2.10/08_jmeter_templates_box.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Workbench can now be saved</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="489" height="198" image="changes/2.10/09_save_workbench.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Syntax color has been added to scripts elements (BeanShell, BSF, and JSR223), MongoDB and JDBC elements making code much more readable and allowing UNDO/REDO through CTRL+Z/CTRL+Y</ch_title>
<p>BSF Sampler with syntax color
<figure width="915" height="620" image="changes/2.10/10_color_syntax_bsf_sampler.png"></figure>
</p>
<p>JSR223 Pre Processor with syntax color
<figure width="911" height="614" image="changes/2.10/11_color_syntax_jsr223_preprocessor.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Better editors are now available for Test Elements with large text content, like HTTP Sampler, and JMS related Test Element providing line numbering and allowing UNDO/REDO through CTRL+Z/CTRL+Y</ch_title>

<ch_title>JMeter GUI can now be fully Internationalized, all remaining issues have been fixed</ch_title>
<h5>Currently French has all its labels translated. Other languages are partly translated, feel free to 
contribute translations by reading <a href="localising/index.html">Localisation (Translator's Guide)</a></h5>

<ch_title>Moving elements in Test plan has been improved in many ways</ch_title>
<h5>Drag and drop of elements in Test Plan tree is now much easier and possible on multiple nodes</h5>
<p>
<figure width="894" height="236" image="changes/2.10/12_drap_n-drop_multiple.png"></figure>
</p>
<p>
<b>Note that due to this <a href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=6560955">bug in Java</a>,
you cannot drop a node after last node. The workaround is to drop it before this last node and then Drag and Drop the last node 
before the one you just dropped.</b>
</p>
<h5>New shortcuts have been added to move elements in the tree. </h5>
<p>(alt + Arrow Up) and (alt + Arrow Down) move the element within the parent node<br/>
(alt + Arrow Left) and (alt + Arrow Right) move the element up and down in the tree depth</p>

<ch_title>Response Time Graph Y axis can now be scaled</ch_title>
<p>
<figure width="947" height="596" image="changes/2.10/13_response_time_graph_y_scale.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>JUnit Sampler gives now more details on configuration errors</ch_title>

<!--  =================== Known bugs =================== -->


<ch_section>Known bugs</ch_section>

<ul>
<li>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</li>

<li>Listeners don't show iteration counts when a If Controller has a condition which is always false from the first iteration (see <bugzilla>52496</bugzilla>).  
A workaround is to add a sampler at the same level as (or superior to) the If Controller.
For example a Test Action sampler with 0 wait time (which doesn't generate a sample),
or a Debug Sampler with all fields set to False (to reduce the sample size).
</li>

<li>Webservice sampler does not consider the HTTP response status to compute the status of a response, thus a response 500 containing a non empty body will be considered as successful, see <bugzilla>54006</bugzilla>.
To workaround this issue, ensure you always read the response and add a Response Assertion checking text inside the response.
</li>

<li>
The numbers that appear to the left of the green box are the number of active threads / total number of threads, 
these only apply to a locally run test; they do not include any threads started on remote systems when using client-server mode, (see <bugzilla>54152</bugzilla>).
</li>

<li>
Note that there is a <a href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=6396599 ">bug in Java</a>
on some Linux systems that manifests itself as the following error when running the test cases or JMeter itself:
<pre>
 [java] WARNING: Couldn't flush user prefs:
 java.util.prefs.BackingStoreException:
 java.lang.IllegalArgumentException: Not supported: indent-number
</pre>
This does not affect JMeter operation. This issue is fixed since Java 7b05.
</li>

<li>
With Java 1.6 and Gnome 3 on Linux systems, the JMeter menu may not work correctly (shift between mouse's click and the menu). 
This is a known Java bug (see  <bugzilla>54477 </bugzilla>). 
A workaround is to use a Java 7 runtime (OpenJDK or Oracle JDK).
</li>

<li>
With Oracle Java 7 and Mac Book Pro Retina Display, the JMeter GUI may look blurry. 
This is a known Java bug, see Bug <a href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=8000629" >JDK-8000629</a>.
A workaround is to use a Java 7 update 40 runtime which fixes this issue.
</li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<ch_section>Incompatible changes</ch_section>

<ul>
<li><b>SMTP Sampler</b> now uses eml file subject if subject field is empty</li>

<li>With this version autoFlush has been turned off on PrintWriter in charge of writing test results. 
This results in improved throughput for intensive tests but can result in more test data loss in case
of JMeter crash (extremely rare). To revert to previous behaviour set <code>jmeter.save.saveservice.autoflush</code> property to <code>true</code>.</li>

<li>
Shortcut for <b>Function Helper Dialog</b> is now <i>CTRL+SHIFT+F1 (CMD + SHIFT + F1 for Mac OS)</i>.
The original key sequence <i>(Ctrl+F1)</i> did not work in some locations (it is consumed by the Java Swing ToolTipManager).
It was therefore necessary to change the shortcut.
</li>

<li>
<b>Webservice (SOAP) Request</b> has been removed by default from GUI as Element is deprecated. (Use <b>HTTP Request</b> 
with <i>Body Data</i>, see also the Template <i>Building a SOAP Webservice Test Plan</i>), if you need to show it, see property <code>not_in_menu</code> in <i>jmeter.properties</i>
</li>

<li>
<b>Transaction Controller</b> now sets <i>Response Code</i> of <i>Generated Parent Sampler</i> 
(if <i>Generated Parent Sampler</i> is checked) to response code of first failing child in case of failure of one of the children, in previous versions <i>Response Code</i> was empty.
</li>

<li>
In previous versions, <b>IncludeController</b> could run Test Elements located inside a <b>Thread Group</b>, this behaviour (<i>which was not documented</i>) 
ould result in weird behaviour, it has been removed in this version (see <bugzilla>55464</bugzilla>). 
The correct way to include Test Elements is to use <b>Test Fragment</b> as stated in documentation of <b>Include Controller</b>.
</li>

<li>
The retry count for the HttpClient 3.1 and HttpClient 4.x samplers has been changed to <b>0</b>.
Previously the default was 1, which could cause unexpected additional traffic.
</li>

<li>Starting with this version, the <b>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder</b> tries to detect when a sample is the result of a previous
redirect. If the current response is a redirect, JMeter will save the redirect URL. When the next request is received, 
it is compared with the saved redirect URL and if there is a match, JMeter will disable the generated sample.
To revert to previous behaviour, set the property <code>proxy.redirect.disabling=false</code>
</li>

<li>Starting with this version, in <b>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder</b> if Grouping is set to <i>Put each group in a new Transaction Controller</i>, 
the Recorder will create <b>Transaction Controller</b> instances with <i>Include duration of timer and pre-post processors in generated sample</i> set 
to false. This default value reflect more accurately response time.
</li>

<li><code>__escapeOroRegexpChars</code> function (which escapes ORO reserved characters) no longer trims the value (see <bugzilla>55328</bugzilla>)
</li>

<li>The <i>commons-lang-2.6.jar</i> has been removed from embedded libraries in <code>jmeter/lib</code> folder as it is not needed by JMeter at run-time
(it is only used by Apache Velocity for generating documentation).
If you use any plugin or third-party code that depends on it, you need to add it in <code>jmeter/lib</code> folder
</li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<ch_section>Bug fixes</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Proxy</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54627</bugzilla> - JMeter Proxy GUI: Type of sampler setting takes the whole screen when there are samplers with long names.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54629</bugzilla> - HTMLParser does not extract &amp;lt;object&amp;gt; tag urls.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55023</bugzilla> - SSL Context reuse feature (51380) adversely affects non-ssl request performance/throughput. based on analysis by Brent Cromarty (brent.cromarty at yahoo.ca)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55092</bugzilla> - Log message "WARN - jmeter.protocol.http.sampler.HTTPSamplerBase: Null URL detected (should not happen)" displayed when embedded resource URL is malformed.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55161</bugzilla> - Useless processing in SoapSampler.setPostHeaders. Contributed by Adrian Nistor (nistor1 at illinois.edu)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54482</bugzilla> - HC fails to follow redirects with non-encoded chars.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54142</bugzilla> - HTTP Proxy Server throws an exception when path contains "|" character.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55388</bugzilla> - HC3 does not allow IP Source field to override httpclient.localaddress.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55450</bugzilla> - HEAD redirects should remain as HEAD</li>
<li><bugzilla>55455</bugzilla> - HTTPS with HTTPClient4 ignores cps setting</li>
<li><bugzilla>55502</bugzilla> - Proxy generates empty http:/ entries when recording</li>
<li><bugzilla>55504</bugzilla> - Proxy incorrectly issues CONNECT requests when browser prompts for certificate override</li>
<li><bugzilla>55506</bugzilla> - Proxy should deliver failed requests to any configured Listeners</li>
<li><bugzilla>55545</bugzilla> - HTTP Proxy Server GUI should not allow both Follow and Auto redirect to be selected</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54913</bugzilla> - JMSPublisherGui incorrectly restores its state. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55027</bugzilla> - Test Action regression, duration value is not recorded (nightly build).</li>
<li><bugzilla>55163</bugzilla> - BeanShellTestElement fails to quote string when calling testStarted(String)/testEnded(String).</li>
<li><bugzilla>55349</bugzilla> - NativeCommand hangs if no input file is specified and the application requests input.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55462</bugzilla> - System Sampler should not change the sampler label if a sample fails</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54467</bugzilla> - Loop Controller: compute loop value only once per parent iteration.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54985</bugzilla> - Make Transaction Controller set Response Code of Generated Parent Sampler to response code of first failing child in case of failure of one of its children. Contributed by Mikhail Epikhin (epihin-m at yandex.ru)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54950</bugzilla> - ModuleController : Changes to referenced Module are not taken into account if changes occur after first run and referenced node is disabled.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55201</bugzilla> - ForEach controller excludes start index and includes end index (clarified documentation).</li>
<li><bugzilla>55334</bugzilla> - Adding Include Controller to test plan (made of Include Controllers) without saving TestPlan leads to included code not being taken into account until save.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55375</bugzilla> -  StackOverflowError with ModuleController in Non-GUI mode if its name is the same as the target node.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55464</bugzilla> - Include Controller running included thread group</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54589</bugzilla> - View Results Tree have a lot of Garbage characters if html page uses double-byte charset.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54753</bugzilla> - StringIndexOutOfBoundsException at SampleResult.getSampleLabel() if key_on_threadname=false when using Statistical mode.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54685</bugzilla> - ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException if "sample_variable" is set in client but not server.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55111</bugzilla> - ViewResultsTree: text not refitted if vertical scrollbar is required. Contributed by Milamber</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54540</bugzilla> - "HTML Parameter Mask" are not marked deprecated in the IHM.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54575</bugzilla> - CSS/JQuery Extractor : Choosing JODD Implementation always uses JSOUP.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54901</bugzilla> - Response Assertion GUI behaves weirdly.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54924</bugzilla> - XMLAssertion uses JMeter JVM file.encoding instead of response encoding and does not clean threadlocal variable.</li>
<li><bugzilla>53679</bugzilla> -  Constant Throughput Timer bug with localization. Reported by Ludovic Garcia</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>55328</bugzilla> - __escapeOroRegexpChars trims spaces.</li>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>55437</bugzilla> - ComboStringEditor does not translate EDIT and UNDEFINED strings on language change</li>
<li><bugzilla>55501</bugzilla> - Incorrect encoding for French description of __char function. Contributed by Antonio Gomes Rodrigues (ra0077 at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54504</bugzilla> - Resource string not found: [clipboard_node_read_error].</li>
<li><bugzilla>54538</bugzilla> - GUI: context menu is too big.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54847</bugzilla> - Cut &amp; Paste is broken with tree multi-selection. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54870</bugzilla> - Tree drag and drop may lose leaf nodes (affected nightly build). Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55056</bugzilla> - wasted work in Data.append(). Contributed by Adrian Nistor (nistor1 at illinois.edu)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55129</bugzilla> -  Change Javadoc generation per CVE-2013-1571, VU#225657.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55187</bugzilla> - Integer overflow when computing ONE_YEAR_MS in HTTP CacheManager.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55208</bugzilla> - JSR223 language entries are duplicated; fold to lower case.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55203</bugzilla> - TestBeanGUI - wrong language settings found.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55065</bugzilla> - Useless processing in Spline3.converge(). Contributed by Adrian Nistor (nistor1 at illinois.edu)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55064</bugzilla> - Useless processing in ReportTreeListener.isValidDragAction(). Contributed by Adrian Nistor (nistor1 at illinois.edu)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55242</bugzilla> - BeanShell Client jar throws exceptions after upgrading to 2.8.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55288</bugzilla> - JMeter should default to 0 retries for HTTP requests.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55405</bugzilla> - ant download_jars task fails if lib/api or lib/doc are missing. Contributed by Antonio Gomes Rodrigues.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55427</bugzilla> - TestBeanHelper should ignore properties not supported by GenericTestBeanCustomizer</li>
<li><bugzilla>55459</bugzilla> - Elements using ComboStringEditor lose the input value if user selects another Test Element</li>
<li><bugzilla>54152</bugzilla> - In distributed testing : activeThreads always show 0 in GUI and Summariser</li>
<li><bugzilla>55509</bugzilla> - Allow Plugins to be notified of remote thread number progression</li>
<li><bugzilla>55572</bugzilla> - Detail popup of parameter does not show a Scrollbar when content exceeds display</li>
<li><bugzilla>55580</bugzilla> -  Help pane does not scroll to start for &lt;a href="#"&gt; links</li>
<li><bugzilla>55600</bugzilla> - JSyntaxTextArea : Strange behaviour on first undo</li>
<li><bugzilla>55655</bugzilla> - NullPointerException when Remote stopping /shutdown all if one engine did not start correctly. Contributed by UBIK Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55657</bugzilla> - Remote and Local Stop/Shutdown buttons state does not take into account local / remote status </li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<ch_section>Improvements</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Proxy</h3>
<ul>
<li>HTTP Request: Small user interaction improvements in Row parameter Detail Box. Contributed by Milamber</li>
<li><bugzilla>55255</bugzilla> - Allow Body in HTTP DELETE method to support API that use it (like ElasticSearch).</li>
<li><bugzilla>53480</bugzilla> - Add Kerberos support to Http Sampler (HttpClient4). Based on patch by Felix Schumacher (felix.schumacher at internetallee.de)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54874</bugzilla> - Support device in addition to source IP address. Based on patch by Dan Fruehauf (malkodan at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55488</bugzilla> - Add .ico and .woff file extension to default suggested exclusions in proxy recorder. Contributed by Antonio Gomes Rodrigues</li>
<li><bugzilla>55525</bugzilla> - Proxy should support alias for keyserver entry</li>
<li><bugzilla>55531</bugzilla> - Proxy recording and redirects. Added code to disable redirected samples.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55507</bugzilla> - Proxy SSL recording does not handle external embedded resources well</li>
<li><bugzilla>55632</bugzilla> - Have a new implementation of htmlParser for embedded resources parsing with better performances</li>
<li><bugzilla>55653</bugzilla> - HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder should set TransactionController property "Include duration of timer and pre-post processors in generated sample" to false</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54788</bugzilla> - JMS Point-to-Point Sampler - GUI enhancements to increase readability and ease of use. Contributed by Bruno Antunes (b.m.antunes at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54798</bugzilla> - Using subject from EML-file for SMTP Sampler. Contributed by Mikhail Epikhin (epihin-m at yandex.ru)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54759</bugzilla> - SSLPeerUnverifiedException using HTTPS , property documented.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54896</bugzilla> - JUnit sampler gives only "failed to create an instance of the class" message with constructor problems.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55084</bugzilla> - Add timeout support for JDBC Request. Contributed by Mikhail Epikhin (epihin-m at yandex.ru)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55403</bugzilla> - Enhancement to OS sampler: Support for timeout</li>
<li><bugzilla>55518</bugzilla> - Add ability to limit number of cached PreparedStatements per connection when "Prepared Select Statement", "Prepared Update Statement" or "Callable Statement" query type is selected</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54271</bugzilla> - Module Controller breaks if test plan is renamed.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54532</bugzilla> - Improve Response Time Graph Y axis scale with huge values or small values (&amp;lt; 1000ms). Add a new field to define increment scale. Contributed by Milamber based on patch by Luca Maragnani (luca.maragnani at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54576</bugzilla> - View Results Tree : Add a CSS/JQuery Tester.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54777</bugzilla> - Improve Performance of default ResultCollector. Based on patch by Mikhail Epikhin (epihin-m at yandex.ru)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55389</bugzilla> - Show IP source address in request data</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54789</bugzilla> - XPath Assertion - GUI enhancements to increase readability and ease of use.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54991</bugzilla> - Add functions to encode/decode URL encoded chars (__urlencode and __urldecode). Contributed by Milamber.</li>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>55241</bugzilla> - Need GUI Editor to process fields which are based on Enums with localised display strings</li>
<li><bugzilla>55440</bugzilla> - ComboStringEditor should allow tags to be language dependent</li>
<li><bugzilla>55432</bugzilla> - CSV Dataset Config loses sharing mode when switching languages</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54584</bugzilla> - MongoDB plugin. Based on patch by Jan Paul Ettles (janpaulettles at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54669</bugzilla> - Add flag forcing non-GUI JVM to exit after test. Contributed by Scott Emmons</li>
<li><bugzilla>42428</bugzilla> - Workbench not saved with Test Plan. Contributed by Dzmitry Kashlach (dzmitrykashlach at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54825</bugzilla> - Add shortcuts to move elements in the tree. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54834</bugzilla> - Improve Drag &amp; Drop in the jmeter tree. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54839</bugzilla> - Set the application name on Mac. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54841</bugzilla> - Correctly handle the quit shortcut on Mac Os (CMD-Q). Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54844</bugzilla> - Set the application icon on Mac Os. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54864</bugzilla> - Enable multi selection drag &amp; drop in the tree without having to start dragging before releasing Shift or Control. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54945</bugzilla> - Add Shutdown Hook to enable trapping kill or CTRL+C signals.</li>
<li><bugzilla>54990</bugzilla> - Download large files avoiding outOfMemory.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55085</bugzilla> - UX Improvement : Ability to create New Test Plan from Templates. Contributed by UBIK Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55172</bugzilla> - Provide plugins a way to add Top Menu and menu items.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55202</bugzilla> - Add syntax color for scripts elements (BeanShell, BSF, and JSR223) and JDBC elements with RSyntaxTextArea. Contributed by Milamber based on patch by Marko Vlahovic (vlahovic74 at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55175</bugzilla> - HTTPHC4Impl refactoring to allow better inheritance.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55236</bugzilla> - Templates - provide button to reload template details.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55237</bugzilla> - Template system should support relative fileName entries.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55423</bugzilla> - BatchSampleSender: Reduce locking granularity by moving listener.processBatch outside of synchronized block</li>
<li><bugzilla>55424</bugzilla> - Add Stripping to existing SampleSenders</li>
<li><bugzilla>55451</bugzilla> - Test Element GUI with JSyntaxTextArea scroll down when text content is long enough to add a Scrollbar</li>
<li><bugzilla>55513</bugzilla> - StreamCopier cannot be used with System.err or System.out as it closes the output stream</li>
<li><bugzilla>55514</bugzilla> - SystemCommand should support arbitrary input and output streams</li>
<li><bugzilla>55515</bugzilla> - SystemCommand should support chaining of commands</li>
<li><bugzilla>55606</bugzilla> - Use JSyntaxtTextArea for Http Request, JMS Test Elements</li>
<li><bugzilla>55651</bugzilla> - Change JMeter application icon to Apache plume icon</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Non-functional changes</ch_section>
<ul>
<li>Updated to jsoup-1.7.2</li>
<li><bugzilla>54776</bugzilla> - Update the dependency on Bouncy Castle to 1.48. Contributed by Emmanuel Bourg (ebourg at apache.org)</li>
<li>Updated to HttpComponents Client 4.2.6 (from 4.2.3)</li>
<li>Updated to HttpComponents Core 4.2.5 (from 4.2.3)</li>
<li>Updated to commons-codec 1.8 (from 1.6)</li>
<li>Updated to commons-io 2.4 (from 2.2)</li>
<li>Updated to commons-logging 1.1.3 (from 1.1.1)</li>
<li>Updated to commons-net 3.3 (from 3.1)</li>
<li>Updated to jdom-1.1.3 (from 1.1.2)</li>
<li>Updated to jodd-lagarto and jodd-core 3.4.8 (from 3.4.1)</li>
<li>Updated to junit 4.11 (from 4.10)</li>
<li>Updated to slf4j-api 1.7.5 (from 1.7.2)</li>
<li>Updated to tika 1.4 (from 1.3)</li>
<li>Updated to xmlgraphics-commons 1.5 (from 1.3.1)</li>
<li>Updated to xstream 1.4.4 (from 1.4.2)</li>
<li>Updated to BouncyCastle 1.49 (from 1.48)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54912</bugzilla> - JMeterTreeListener should use constants. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54903</bugzilla> - Remove the dependency on the Activation Framework. Contributed by Emmanuel Bourg (ebourg at apache.org)</li>
<li>Moved commons-lang (2.6) to lib/doc as it's only needed by Velocity.</li>
<li>Re-organised and simplified NOTICE and LICENSE files.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55411</bugzilla> -  NativeCommand could be useful elsewhere. Copied code to o.a.jorphan.exec.</li>
<li><bugzilla>55435</bugzilla> - ComboStringEditor could be simplified to make most settings final</li>
<li><bugzilla>55436</bugzilla> - ComboStringEditor should implement ClearGui</li>
<li><bugzilla>55463</bugzilla> - Component.requestFocus() is discouraged; use requestFocusInWindow() instead</li>
<li><bugzilla>55486</bugzilla> - New JMeter Logo. Contributed by UBIK Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55548</bugzilla> - Tidy up use of TestElement.ENABLED; use TestElement.isEnabled()/setEnabled() throughout</li>
<li><bugzilla>55617</bugzilla> - Improvements to jorphan collection. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bugzilla>55623</bugzilla> - Invalid/unexpected configuration values should not be silently ignored</li>
<li><bugzilla>55626</bugzilla> - Rename HTTP Proxy Server as HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Thanks</ch_section>
<p>We thank all contributors mentioned in bug and improvement sections above.<br/>
We also thank bug reporters who helped us improve JMeter. <br/>
For this release we want to give special thanks to the following reporters for the clear reports and tests made after our fixes:
<ul>
<li>Immanuel Hayden (immanuel.hayden at gmail.com)</li>
<li>Danny Lade (dlade at web.de)</li>
<li>Brent Cromarty (brent.cromarty at yahoo.ca)</li>
<li>Wolfgang Heider (wolfgang.heider at racon.at)</li>
<li>Shmuel Krakower (shmulikk at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

Apologies if we have omitted anyone else.
 </p>
</section> 
</body> 
</document>
