<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>   
<properties>     
    <author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>     
    <title>Changes</title>   
</properties> 
<body> 
<section name="Changes"> 
<style type="text/css"><!--
h2 { color: #960000; }
h3 { color: #960000; }
--></style>
<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 2.13 =================== -->

<h1>Version 2.13</h1>

Summary
<ul>
<li><a href="#New and Noteworthy">New and Noteworthy</a></li>
<li><a href="#Known bugs">Known bugs</a></li>
<li><a href="#Incompatible changes">Incompatible changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Bug fixes">Bug fixes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Improvements">Improvements</a></li>
<li><a href="#Non-functional changes">Non-functional changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Thanks">Thanks</a></li>

</ul>

<ch_section>New and Noteworthy</ch_section>

<!-- <ch_category>Improvements</ch_category> -->
<!-- <ch_title>Sample title</ch_title>
<p>
<ul>
<li>Sample text</li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_title>Sample title</ch_title>
<p>Sample text</p>
<figure width="691" height="215" image="changes/2.10/18_https_test_script_recorder.png"></figure>
 -->

<ch_category>New Elements</ch_category>

<ch_title>New Async BackendListener with Graphite implementation</ch_title>
<p>A new Async BackendListener has been added to allow sending result data to a backend listener. 
JMeter ships with a GraphiteBackendListenerClient that allows sending results to a <a href="http://graphite.wikidot.com/" target="_blank">Graphite</a> server using Pickle ot Plaintext protocols.
You can implement your own backend by extending <a href="./api/org/apache/jmeter/visualizers/backend/AbstractBackendListenerClient.html">AbstractBackendListenerClient</a>. This backend could be 
a database (JDBC), a Message Oriented Middleware (JMS), a Webservice or anything you want.
 </p>
<figure width="902" height="293" image="changes/2.13/backend_listener_graphite.png"></figure>
<p>This is the kind of Live Dashboard you can obtain using <a href="http://grafana.org/" target="_blank" >Grafana</a> and <a href="http://influxdb.com/" target="_blank" >InfluxDB</a><br/>
Read <a href="./usermanual/realtime-results.html" >this</a> for more details.</p>
<figure width="1265" height="581" image="grafana_dashboard.png">Grafana dashboard</figure>

<ch_category>Core Improvements</ch_category>

<ch_title>New connect time metric</ch_title>
<p>Starting with this version a new metric called connectTime has been added. It represents the time to establish connection.
By default it is not saved to CSV or XML, to have it saved add to user.properties:<br/>
<code>
jmeter.save.saveservice.connect_time=true
</code>
</p>
<figure width="1058" height="193" image="changes/2.13/connect_time_table.png"></figure>
<figure width="665" height="651" image="changes/2.13/connect_time_tree.png"></figure>

<ch_title>Aggregate Graph and Report</ch_title>
<p>The listeners Aggregate Graph and Aggregate Report previously showed only the 90 percentile (historical behavior), the 95 percentile and the 99 percentile have been added and are customizable.
To setup the percentiles value you want, add to user.properties:<br/>
<code>
aggregate_rpt_pct1=90<br/>
aggregate_rpt_pct2=95<br/>
aggregate_rpt_pct3=99
</code>
<figure width="801" height="681" image="changes/2.13/aggregate_graph_new_percentile.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder</ch_title>
<p>Now component is able to detect authentication schemes and automatically adds a pre-configured HTTP Authorization Manager with the correct Mechanism.
</p>

<ch_title>HTTP Request</ch_title>
<p>The CalDAV verbs (Calendar extensions to WebDAV) REPORT and MKCALENDAR have been added in the HTTP Request sampler.
<figure width="716" height="324" image="changes/2.13/new_methods_caldav.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>JDBC Request</ch_title>
<p>The ResultSet can be get as a object, this allows to handle more easily the results after in BeanShell, JSR223 scripts...
<figure width="683" height="628" image="changes/2.13/jdbc_resultset_handler.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Distributed Testing</ch_title>
<p>To allow better usage of Distributed Testing in the cloud, retry behaviour has been added when starting test on servers.
Read <a href="./usermanual/remote-test.html#retries" >this</a> for more details.
<figure width="669" height="202" image="changes/2.13/distributed_retry.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Distributed Testing performance</ch_title>
<p>Since JMeter 2.13, Stripping modes (StrippingBatch being the default mode) now also strip responses from SubResults improving consumed network bandwidth.
</p>

<ch_title>Documentation refresh</ch_title>
<p>A new style for website (responsive and more up to date) has been created by Felix Schumacher.
Documentations have been refreshed particularly:
<ul>
    <li><a href="./usermanual/build-ws-test-plan.html">Building a Webservice Test Plan</a></li>
    <li><a href="./usermanual/best-practices.html">Best Practices</a></li>
    <li><a href="./usermanual/boss.html">Help! My boss wants me to load test our application!</a></li>
</ul>
</p>

<ch_category>GUI Improvements</ch_category>

<ch_title>Module Controller</ch_title>
<p>The Module Controller now shows the target controller in a tree view (instead of combo list).
<figure width="306" height="372" image="changes/2.13/module_controller_tree_view.png"></figure>
</p>

<ch_title>Toolbar</ch_title>
<p>JMeter's toolbar has been refreshed for some icons (start, toogle, etc.). Three sizes are now avialable for the icons: 22x22, 32x32 and 48x48.<br>
The property to define your prefered size is:
<pre>jmeter.toolbar.icons.size=value</pre>
with the value 22x22 (default size), 32x32 or 48x48.</br></p>
<p>The toolbar with 22x22 pixels icons
<figure width="417" height="116" image="changes/2.13/toolbar_22x22.png"></figure>
</p>

<p>The toolbar with 32x32 pixels icons
<figure width="533" height="130" image="changes/2.13/toolbar_32x32.png"></figure>
</p>

<p>The toolbar with 48x48 pixels icons
<figure width="716" height="143" image="changes/2.13/toolbar_48x48.png"></figure>
</p>
 
<ch_title>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder</ch_title>
<p>If your Test Plan does not contains a Recording Controller, a new warning message will appear if the
 HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder is configured to send the samples into a Recording Controller.
<figure width="858" height="386" image="changes/2.13/warning_message_proxy.png"></figure>
</p>

<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<ch_section>Incompatible changes</ch_section>

<ul>
    <li>Since 2.13, Aggregate Graph, Summary Report and Aggregate Report now export percentages to %, before they exported the decimal value which differed from what was shown in GUI</li>
    <li>Third party plugins may be impacted by fix of <bugzilla>57586</bugzilla>, ensure that your subclass of HttpTestSampleGui implements ItemListener if you relied on parent class doing so.</li>
    <li>Report package has been removed, ApacheJMeter_report.jar is not generated anymore as a consequence, see <bugzilla>57269</bugzilla></li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<ch_section>Improvements</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>25430</bug>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder : Make it populate HTTP Authorization Manager. Partly based on a patch from Dzmitry Kashlach (dzmitrykashlach at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bug>57381</bug>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder should display an error if Target Controller references a Recording Controller and no Recording Controller exists. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57488</bug>Performance : Improve SSLContext reset for Two-way SSL Authentication</li>
<li><bug>57565</bug>SamplerCreator : Add method to allow implementations to add children to created sampler</li>
<li><bug>57606</bug>HTTPSamplerBase#errorResult changes the sample label on exception </li>
<li><bug>57613</bug>HTTP Sampler : Added CalDAV verbs (REPORT, MKCALENDAR). Contributed by Richard Brigham (richard.brigham at teamaol.com)</li>
<li><bug>48799</bug>Add time to establish connection to available sample metrics. Implemented by Andrey Pokhilko (andrey at blazemeter.com) and contributed by BlazeMeter Ltd. and Pieter Ennes (apache.org at spam.ennes.nl)</li>
<li><bug>57500</bug>Introduce retry behavior for distributed testing. Implemented by Andrey Pokhilko and Dzimitry Kashlach and contributed by BlazeMeter Ltd.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>57322</bug>JDBC Test elements: add ResultHandler to deal with ResultSets(cursors) returned by callable statements. Contributed by Yngvi &amp;THORN;&amp;oacute;r Sigurj&amp;oacute;nsson (blitzkopf at gmail.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57561</bug>Module controller UI : Replace combobox by tree. Contributed by Maciej Franek (maciej.franek at gmail.com)</li>
<li><bug>57648</bug>TestFragment should be disabled when created. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>55932</bug>Create a Async BackendListener to allow easy plug of new listener (Graphite, JDBC, Console,...)</li>
<li><bug>57246</bug>BackendListener : Create a Graphite implementation</li>
<li><bug>57217</bug>Aggregate graph and Aggregate report improvements (3 configurable percentiles, same data in both, factor out code). Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57537</bug>BackendListener : Allow implementations to drop samples</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>54453</bug>Performance enhancements : Replace Random by ThreadLocalRandom in __Random function</li>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57518</bug>Icons for toolbar with several sizes</li>
<li><bug>57605</bug>When there is an error loading Test Plan, SaveService.loadTree returns null leading to NPE in callers</li>
<li><bug>57269</bug>Drop org.apache.jmeter.reports package</li>
<li><bug>53764</bug>Website : Create a new style for website</li>
</ul>
<ch_section>Non-functional changes</ch_section>
<ul>
<li>Updated to jsoup-1.8.1.jar (from 1.7.3)</li>
<li>Updated to tika-core and tika-parsers 1.7 (from 1.6)</li>
<li>Updated to commons-codec-1.10.jar (from 1.9)</li>
<li>Updated to dnsjava-2.1.7.jar (from 2.1.6)</li>
<li>Updated to jodd-3.6.4.jar (from 3.6.1)</li>
<li>Updated to junit-4.12.jar (from 4.11)</li>
<li>Updated to rhino-1.7R5 (from 1.7R4)</li>
<li>Updated to rsyntaxtextarea-2.5.6 (from 2.5.3)</li>
<li>Updated to slf4j-1.7.10 (from 1.7.5)</li>
<li><bug>57276</bug>RMIC no longer needed since Java 5</li>
<li><bug>57310</bug>Replace System.getProperty("file.separator") with File.separator throughout (Also "path.separator" with File.pathSeparator)</li>
<li><bug>57389</bug>Fix potential NPE in converters</li>
<li><bug>57417</bug>Remove unused method isTemporary from NullProperty. This was a leftover from a refactoring done in 2003.</li>
<li><bug>57418</bug>Remove unused constructor from Workbench</li>
<li><bug>57419</bug>Remove unused interface ModelListener.</li>
<li><bug>57466</bug>IncludeController : Remove an unneeded set creation. Contributed by Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li>Added property loggerpanel.usejsyntaxtext to disable the use of JSyntaxTextArea for the Console Logger (in case of memory or other issues)</li>
<li><bug>57586</bug>HttpTestSampleGui: Remove interface ItemListener implementation</li>
</ul>
 
 <!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<ch_section>Bug fixes</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57385</bug>Getting empty thread name in xml result for HTTP requests with "Follow Redirects" set. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57579</bug>NullPointerException error is raised on main sample if "RETURN_NO_SAMPLE" is used (default) and "Use Cache-Control / Expires header..." is checked in HTTP Cache Manager</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57447</bug>Use only the user listed DNS Servers, when "use custom DNS resolver" option is enabled.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57262</bug>Aggregate Report, Aggregate Graph and Summary Report export : headers use keys instead of labels</li>
<li><bug>57346</bug>Summariser : The + (difference) reports show wrong elapsed time and throughput</li>
<li><bug>57449</bug>Distributed Testing: Stripped modes do not strip responses from SubResults (affects load tests that use Download of embedded resources). Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57562</bug>View Results Tree CSS/JQuery Tester : Nothing happens when there is an error in syntax and an exception occurs in jmeter.log</li>
<li><bug>57514</bug>Aggregate Graph, Summary Report and Aggregate Report show wrong percentage reporting in saved file</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57607</bug>Constant Throughput Timer : Wrong throughput computed in shared modes due to rounding error </li>
</ul>
<!-- 
<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>
 -->
<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bug>57365</bug>Selected LAF is not correctly setup due to call of UIManager.setLookAndFeel too late. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57364</bug>Options &lt; Look And Feel does not update all windows LAF. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
<li><bug>57394</bug>When constructing an instance with ClassTools#construct(String, int) the integer was ignored and the default constructor was used instead.</li>
<li><bug>57440</bug>OutOfMemoryError after introduction of JSyntaxTextArea in LoggerPanel due to disableUndo not being taken into account.</li>
<li><bug>57569</bug>FileServer.reserveFile - inconsistent behaviour when hasHeader is true</li>
<li><bug>57555</bug>Cannot use JMeter 2.12 as a maven dependency. Contributed by Pascal Schumacher (pascal.schumacher at t-systems.com)</li>
<li><bug>57608</bug>Fix start script compatibility with old Unix shells, e.g. on Solaris</li>
</ul>

 <!--  =================== Thanks =================== -->

<ch_section>Thanks</ch_section>
<p>We thank all contributors mentioned in bug and improvement sections above:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://ubikloadpack.com">Ubik Load Pack</a></li>
<li>Yngvi &amp;THORN;&amp;oacute;r Sigurj&amp;oacute;nsson (blitzkopf at gmail.com)</li>
<li>Dzmitry Kashlach (dzmitrykashlach at gmail.com)</li>
<li><a href="http://blazemeter.com">BlazeMeter Ltd.</a></li>
<li>Benoit Wiart (benoit.wiart at gmail.com)</li>
<li>Pascal Schumacher (pascal.schumacher at t-systems.com)</li>
<li>Maciej Franek (maciej.franek at gmail.com)</li>
<li>Richard Brigham (richard.brigham at teamaol.com)</li>
<li>Pieter Ennes (apache.org at spam.ennes.nl)</li>
</ul>

<br/>
We also thank bug reporters who helped us improve JMeter. <br/>
For this release we want to give special thanks to the following reporters for the clear reports and tests made after our fixes:
<ul>
<li>Chaitanya Bhatt (bhatt.chaitanya at gmail.com) for his thorough testing of new BackendListener and Graphite Client implementation.</li>
<li>Marcelo Jara (marcelojara at hotmail.com) for his clear report on <bugzilla>57607</bugzilla>.</li>
</ul>

Apologies if we have omitted anyone else.
 </p>
 <!--  =================== Known bugs =================== -->
 
<ch_section>Known bugs</ch_section>

<ul>
<li>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</li>

<li>
The numbers that appear to the left of the green box are the number of active threads / total number of threads, 
the total number of threads only applies to a locally run test, otherwise it will show 0 (see <bugzilla>55510</bugzilla>).
</li>

<li>
Note that there is a <a href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=6396599 ">bug in Java</a>
on some Linux systems that manifests itself as the following error when running the test cases or JMeter itself:
<pre>
 [java] WARNING: Couldn't flush user prefs:
 java.util.prefs.BackingStoreException:
 java.lang.IllegalArgumentException: Not supported: indent-number
</pre>
This does not affect JMeter operation. This issue is fixed since Java 7b05.
</li>

<li>
Note that under some windows systems you may have this WARNING:
<pre>
java.util.prefs.WindowsPreferences 
WARNING: Could not open/create prefs root node Software\JavaSoft\Prefs at root 0
x80000002. Windows RegCreateKeyEx(...) returned error code 5.
</pre>
The fix is to run JMeter as Administrator, it will create the registry key for you, then you can restart JMeter as a normal user and you won't have the warning anymore.
</li>

<li>
With Java 1.6 and Gnome 3 on Linux systems, the JMeter menu may not work correctly (shift between mouse's click and the menu). 
This is a known Java bug (see  <bugzilla>54477</bugzilla>). 
A workaround is to use a Java 7 runtime (OpenJDK or Oracle JDK).
</li>

<li>
With Oracle Java 7 and Mac Book Pro Retina Display, the JMeter GUI may look blurry. 
This is a known Java bug, see Bug <a href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=8000629" >JDK-8000629</a>.
A workaround is to use a Java 7 update 40 runtime which fixes this issue.
</li>

<li>
You may encounter the following error: <i>java.security.cert.CertificateException: Certificates does not conform to algorithm constraints</i>
 if you run a HTTPS request on a web site with a SSL certificate (itself or one of SSL certificates in its chain of trust) with a signature
 algorithm using MD2 (like md2WithRSAEncryption) or with a SSL certificate with a size lower than 1024 bits.
This error is related to increased security in Java 7 version u16 (MD2) and version u40 (Certificate size lower than 1024 bits), and Java 8 too.
<br></br>
To allow you to perform your HTTPS request, you can downgrade the security of your Java installation by editing 
the Java <b>jdk.certpath.disabledAlgorithms</b> property. Remove the MD2 value or the constraint on size, depending on your case.
<br></br>
This property is in this file:
<pre>JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/java.security</pre>
See  <bugzilla>56357</bugzilla> for details.
</li>

</ul>
 
</section> 
</body> 
</document>
