<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document
[
<!ENTITY hellip   "&#x02026;" >
<!ENTITY rarr     "&#x02192;" >
<!ENTITY vellip   "&#x022EE;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp     "&#x00A0;" >
]>
<document>
<properties>
    <author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>
    <title>Changes</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Changes">
<style type="text/css"><!--
h2 { color: #960000; }
h3 { color: #960000; }
--></style>
<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 5.2 =================== -->

<h1>Version 5.2</h1>
<p>
Summary
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#New and Noteworthy">New and Noteworthy</a></li>
<li><a href="#Incompatible changes">Incompatible changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Bug fixes">Bug fixes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Improvements">Improvements</a></li>
<li><a href="#Non-functional changes">Non-functional changes</a></li>
<li><a href="#Known problems and workarounds">Known problems and workarounds</a></li>
<li><a href="#Thanks">Thanks</a></li>

</ul>

<ch_section>New and Noteworthy</ch_section>
<p>
This release is a major release. Please see the <a href="changes_history.html">Changes history page</a>
to view the last release notes of version 5.1.1.
</p>
<!--
<ch_title>Core improvements</ch_title>
<ch_title>UX improvements</ch_title>
<ch_title>Test Plan</ch_title>
<ch_title>Scripting / Debugging enhancements</ch_title>
-->
<!--
<ch_title>Functions</ch_title>
-->
<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<ch_section>Incompatible changes</ch_section>
<ul>
    <li>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder now appends number at end of names, while previously it added it at beginning. See <bugzilla>63450</bugzilla></li>
    <li>When using XPath Assertion with an XPath expression returning a boolean, <code>True if nothing matches</code> had no effect and always returned true, see <bugzilla>63455</bugzilla></li>
    <li>XML parsing now refuses unsecure XML, this has impacts on the following features:
        <ul>
            <li>XMLAssertion</li>
            <li>XMLSchemAssertion</li>
            <li>XPath function</li>
            <li>XPath 1 &amp; 2 Extractors</li>
            <li>XPath 1 &amp; 2 Assertions</li>
        </ul>
    
     </li>
</ul>
<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<ch_section>Improvements</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63450</bug>HTTP(S) Test Script Recorder: Put number at end instead of beginning</li>
    <li><bug>63790</bug>Embedded Resources download: Optimize CSS parsing by removing source location</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63406</bug>JDBC connection configuration: new option for pre-initialize to initialize the connection pool. Contributed by Franz Schwab (franz.schwab@exasol.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63561</bug>JDBC Request: Allow to only fetch a certain number of rows. Contributed by Franz Schwab (franz.schwab@exasol.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63801</bug>Add Bolt protocol support for Neo4j database. Contributed by GraphAware (www.graphaware.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63565</bug>If Controller: GC issue with JMeter during the endurance run when using with "Interpret Condition as Variable Expression?" unchecked => Improve documentation</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63720</bug>BackendListener: InfluxDBBackendListenerClient Add support for InfluxDB 2. Contributed by Jakub Bednář (https://github.com/bednar)</li>
    <li><bug>63770</bug>View Results Tree: Add JMESPath Tester. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
  <li><bug>62863</bug>Enable PKCS11 keystores for usage with KeyStore Manager. Based on patch by Clifford Harms (clifford.harms at gmail.com).</li>
  <li><pr>457</pr>Slight performance improvement in PoissonRandomTimer by using ThreadLocalRandom. Based on a patch by Xia Li.</li>
  <li><bug>62787</bug>New <code>XPath2 Assertion</code> supporting XPath2 with better performances than <code>XPath Assertion</code>. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
  <li><bug>63643</bug>Skip BOM on files opened through <code>FileServer</code> and use the BOM to detect the character encoding,
      if none is given explicitly. Reported by Havlicek Honza (havlicek.honza at gmail.com)</li>
  <li><bug>63727</bug>New <code>JMESPath Extractor</code> element to ease extraction from JSON using <a href="http://jmespath.org">JMESPath</a> technology. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
  <li><bug>63763</bug>New <code>JMESPath Assertion</code> element to ease assertion on JSON using <a href="http://jmespath.org">JMESPath</a> technology. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
  <li><bug>63775</bug>Allow Boundary Extractor to accept empty boundaries</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
  <li><bug>63219</bug>New function <code>__StringToFile</code> to save/append a string into a file. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
  <li>Use <code>AtomicInteger</code> for <code>__counter</code> instead of synchronization on our own</li>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Report / Dashboard</h3>
<ul>
  <li><bug>63471</bug><code>StringConverter</code>s used for report generation should ignore white space around numbers.</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63396</bug>JSR223 Test Elements: Description of Parameters is misleading, same for Script</li>
    <li><bug>63480</bug>XPathAssertion and XPathAssertion2: Improve test coverage for input coming from variable. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63452</bug>Tools / Import from cURL: Complete coverage of all command line options that are valid in JMeter use case. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63419</bug>Tools / Import from cURL: Add ability to import a set of cURL commands from a file. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63760</bug>JOrphanUtils: add random alphanumeric password generator</li>
    <li><bug>63355</bug>View Results Tree: Browser view option is not Available since Java 11, document how to make it available, see <a href="./usermanual/hints_and_tips.html#browser_renderer_view_results_tree">this</a></li>
    <li><bug>62861</bug>Thread Group: Provide ability to configure whether a new iteration is a new user or same user (Would be applied on Cookie Manager, Cache Manager and httpclient.reset_state_on_thread_group_iteration). Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63616</bug>Fix Javadoc: <source>JMeterContext#getThreadNum()</source> starts at 0 and not 1. Contributed by Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Updated to httpclient/httpmime 4.5.10 (from 4.5.7)</li>
    <li>Updated to dnsjava 2.1.9 (from 2.1.8)</li>
    <li>Updated to jsoup 1.12.1 (from 1.11.3)</li>
    <li>Updated to rsyntaxtextarea 3.0.4 (from 3.0.2)</li>
    <li>Updated to caffeine 2.8.0 (from 2.6.2)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-codec 1.13 (from 1.11)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-lang3 3.9 (from 3.8.1)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-pool 2.7 (from 2.6)</li>
    <li>Updated to commons-text 1.8 (from 1.6)</li>
    <li>Updated to freemarker 2.3.29 (from 2.3.28)</li>
    <li>Updated to httpcore/httpcore-nio 4.12 (from 4.11)</li>
    <li>Updated to jodd 5.0.13 (from 5.0.6)</li>
    <li>Updated to log4j 2.12.1 (from 2.11.1)</li>
    <li>Updated to ph-commons 9.3.7 (from 9.2.1)</li>
    <li>Updated to ph-css 6.2.0 (from 6.1.1)</li>
    <li>Updated to Mozilla Rhino 1.7.11 (from 1.7.10)</li>
    <li>Updated to Saxon-HE 9.9.1-5 (from 9.9.1-1)</li>
    <li>Updated to slf4j 1.7.28 (from 1.7.25)</li>
    <li>Updated to tika-core and tika-parsers 1.22 (from 1.21)</li>
    <li>Updated jackson-annotations, jackson-core and jackson-databind to 2.9.10 (from 2.9.8)</li>
</ul>

<ch_section>Non-functional changes</ch_section>
<ul>
    <li>Migrated from subversion to <a href="https://github.com/apache/jmeter">Git</a></li>
    <li><bug>63630</bug>Switch build from Apache Ant to Gradle</li>
    <li><bug>63529</bug>Add more unit tests for org.apache.jorphan.util.JOrphanUtils. Contributed by John Bergqvist(John.Bergqvist at diffblue.com)</li>
    <li>Updated to latest checkstyle (version 8.22)</li>
    <li>Clean-up of code in <code>CompareAssertion</code> and other locations. Based on patch by Graham Russell (graham at ham1.co.uk)</li>
    <li><pr>491</pr>Increase Graphite metrics coverage. Contributed by Graham Russell (graham at ham1.co.uk)</li>
    <li><pr>520</pr>Replace anonymous classes with lambda expressions. Contributed by Graham Russell (graham at ham1.co.uk).</li>
    <li><pr>524</pr>Migration from JUnit 4 to JUnit 5. Contributed by Graham Russell (graham at ham1.co.uk).</li>
</ul>

 <!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<ch_section>Bug fixes</ch_section>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Test Script Recorder</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63298</bug>HTTP Requests with encoded URLs are being sent in decoded format</li>
    <li><bug>63364</bug>When setting <code>subresults.disable_renaming=true</code>, sub results are still renamed using their parent SampleLabel while they shouldn't. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63129</bug>JMeter can not identify encoding during first time page submission. Based partly on analysis and PR made by Naveen Nandwani (naveen.nandwani at india.nec.com)</li>
    <li><bug>62672</bug>HTTP Request sends double requests when using proxy with authentication. Based on patch by Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com) and contributed by BlazeMeter.</li>
    <li><bug>63574</bug>HTTP Cache Manager does not cache resource if <code>Cache-Control</code> header is missing.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63442</bug>Reduce scanning for <code>LogParser</code> implementations in AccessLogSamplerBeanInfo.</li>
    <li><bug>63563</bug>LdapExtSampler: When sampler fails with exception differing from NamingException, no SampleResult is generated</li>
    <li><bug>63469</bug>JMSPublisher: Race condition in jms.client.ClientPool#clearClient</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63319</bug><code>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</code> in Aggregate Graph when selecting 90&nbsp;% or 95&nbsp;% columns</li>
    <li><bug>63423</bug>Selection of table rows in Aggregate Graph gets lost too often</li>
    <li><bug>63347</bug>View result tree: The search field is so small that even a single character is not visible on Windows 7</li>
    <li><bug>63433</bug>ListenerNotifier: Detected problem in Listener NullPointerException if filename is null. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63674</bug>Strip results with subresults deeper in their hierarchy when DataStripping is enabled</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63455</bug>XPath Assertion: <code>True if nothing matches</code> does not work if XPath expression returns a boolean. Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Report / Dashboard</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Documentation</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63513</bug>Add MariaDB examples to JDBC documentation. Contributed by Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63484</bug>Add notes to use Apache Velocity as JSR223 script language. Based on a patch by Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63519</bug><pr>471</pr>Use correct method <code>getLabelResource()</code> in JMeter tutorial. Contributed by Sun Tao (buzzerrookie at hotmail.com>)</li>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
    <li><bug>63394</bug>JMeter should fail with non-zero when test execution fails (due to missing test plan or other reason). Contributed by Ubik Load Pack (support at ubikloadpack.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63464</bug>image/svg+xml is wrongly considered as binary</li>
    <li><bug>63490</bug>At end of scheduler duration lots of Samplers gets executed at the same time</li>
    <li><pr>480</pr><pr>482</pr>Fix a few typos in comments and log messages. Based on patch by Anass Benomar (anassbenomar at gmail.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63751</bug>Correct a typo in Chinese translations. Reported by Jinliang Wang (wjl31802 at 126.com)</li>
    <li><bug>63723</bug>Distributed testing: JMeter master ends distributed test though some threads still are active</li>
    <li><bug>63614</bug>Distributed testing: Unable to generate Dashboard report at end of load test</li>
    <li><bug>63793</bug>Fix unsecure XML Parsing</li>
</ul>

 <!--  =================== Thanks =================== -->

<ch_section>Thanks</ch_section>
<p>We thank all contributors mentioned in bug and improvement sections above:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Clifford Harms (clifford.harms at gmail.com)</li>
  <li><a href="https://ubikloadpack.com">Ubik Load Pack</a></li>
  <li>Xia Li</li>
  <li>Naveen Nandwani (naveen.nandwani at india.nec.com)</li>
  <li>Artem Fedorov (artem.fedorov at blazemeter.com)</li>
  <li>Ori Marko (orimarko at gmail.com)</li>
  <li>Sun Tao (buzzerrookie at hotmail.com)</li>
  <li>John Bergqvist (John.Bergqvist at diffblue.com)</li>
  <li>Franz Schwab (franz.schwab at exasol.com)</li>
  <li>Graham Russell (graham at ham1.co.uk)</li>
  <li>Anass Benomar (anassbenomar at gmail.com)</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bednar">Jakub Bednář</a></li>
  <li>Pascal Schumacher (pascalschumacher at apache.org)</li>
  <li><a href="https://graphaware.com/">GraphAware</a></li>
</ul>
<p>We also thank bug reporters who helped us improve JMeter.</p>
<ul>
    <li>Sergiy Iampol (sergiy.iampol at playtech.com)</li>
    <li>Brian Tully (brian.tully at acquia.com)</li>
    <li>Amer Ghazal (amerghazal at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Stefan Seide (stefan at trilobyte-se.de)</li>
    <li>Havlicek Honza (havlicek.honza at gmail.com)</li>
    <li>Pierre Astruc (pierre.astruc at evertest.com)</li>
    <li>Jinliang Wang (wjl31802 at 126.com)</li>
</ul>
<p>
Apologies if we have omitted anyone else.
</p>
 <!--  =================== Known bugs or issues related to JAVA Bugs =================== -->

<ch_section>Known problems and workarounds</ch_section>
<ul>
<li>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</li>

<li>
The numbers that appear to the left of the green box are the number of active threads / total number of threads,
the total number of threads only applies to a locally run test, otherwise it will show <code>0</code> (see <bugzilla>55510</bugzilla>).
</li>

<li>
Note that under some windows systems you may have this WARNING:
<source>
java.util.prefs.WindowsPreferences
WARNING: Could not open/create prefs root node Software\JavaSoft\Prefs at root 0
x80000002. Windows RegCreateKeyEx(&hellip;) returned error code 5.
</source>
The fix is to run JMeter as Administrator, it will create the registry key for you, then you can restart JMeter as a normal user and you won't have the warning anymore.
</li>

<li>
You may encounter the following error:
<source>java.security.cert.CertificateException: Certificates does not conform to algorithm constraints</source>
 if you run a HTTPS request on a web site with a SSL certificate (itself or one of SSL certificates in its chain of trust) with a signature
 algorithm using MD2 (like <code>md2WithRSAEncryption</code>) or with a SSL certificate with a size lower than 1024 bits.
This error is related to increased security in Java 8+.
<br></br>
To allow you to perform your HTTPS request, you can downgrade the security of your Java installation by editing
the Java <code>jdk.certpath.disabledAlgorithms</code> property. Remove the MD2 value or the constraint on size, depending on your case.
<br></br>
This property is in this file:
<source>JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/java.security</source>
See  <bugzilla>56357</bugzilla> for details.
</li>

<li>
Under Mac OSX Aggregate Graph will show wrong values due to mirroring effect on numbers.
This is due to a known Java bug, see Bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8065373" >JDK-8065373</a>
The fix is to use JDK8_u45 or later.
</li>

<li>
View Results Tree may fail to display some HTML code under HTML renderer, see <bugzilla>54586</bugzilla>.
This is due to a known Java bug which fails to parse "<code>px</code>" units in row/col attributes.
See Bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8031109" >JDK-8031109</a>
The fix is to use JDK9 b65 or later.
</li>

<li>
JTable selection with keyboard (<keycombo><keysym>SHIFT</keysym><keysym>up/down</keysym></keycombo>) is totally unusable with Java 7 on Mac OSX.
This is due to a known Java bug <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.java.net/browse/JDK-8025126" >JDK-8025126</a>
The fix is to use JDK 8 b132 or later.
</li>

<li>
Since Java 11 the JavaScript implementation <a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/335">Nashorn has been deprecated</a>.
Java will emit the following deprecation warnings, if you are using JavaScript based on Nashorn.
<source>
Warning: Nashorn engine is planned to be removed from a future JDK release
</source>
To silence these warnings, add <code>-Dnashorn.args=--no-deprecation-warning</code> to your Java arguments.
That can be achieved by setting the enviroment variable <code>JVM_ARGS</code>
<source>
export JVM_ARGS="-Dnashorn.args=--no-deprecation-warning"
</source>
</li>
</ul>

</section>
</body>
</document>
