<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>   
<properties>     
    <author email="dev AT jmeter.apache.org">JMeter developers</author>     
    <title>Changes</title>   
</properties> 
<body> 
<section name="Changes"> 

<note>
<b>This page details the changes made in the current version only.</b>
<br></br>
Earlier changes are detailed in the <a href="changes_history.html">History of Previous Changes</a>.
</note>


<!--  =================== 2.9 =================== -->

<h1>Version 2.9</h1>

<h2>New and Noteworthy</h2>

<h3>Core Improvements:</h3>
<h4>Webservice sampler now adds to request the headers that are set through Header Manager</h4>

<h3>GUI and ergonomy Improvements:</h3>
<h4>Allow copy from clipboard to HeaderPanel, headers are supposed to be separated by new line and have the following form name:value</h4>

<h4>Proxy now has a button to add a set of default exclusions for URL patterns, this list can be configured through property : proxy.excludes.suggested</h4>

<!--  =================== Known bugs =================== -->

<h2>Known bugs</h2>

<p>The Once Only controller behaves correctly under a Thread Group or Loop Controller,
but otherwise its behaviour is not consistent (or clearly specified).</p>

<p>Listeners don't show iteration counts when a If Controller has a condition which is always false from the first iteration (see <bugzilla>52496</bugzilla>).  
A workaround is to add a sampler at the same level as (or superior to) the If Controller.
For example a Test Action sampler with 0 wait time (which doesn't generate a sample),
or a Debug Sampler with all fields set to False (to reduce the sample size).
</p>

<p>Webservice sampler does not consider the HTTP response status to compute the status of a response, thus a response 500 containing a non empty body will be considered as successful, see <bugzilla>54006</bugzilla>.
To workaround this issue, ensure you always read the response and add a Response Assertion checking text inside the response.
</p>

<p>
Changing language can break part of the configuration of the following elements (see <bugzilla>53679</bugzilla>):
<ul>
    <li>CSV Data Set Config (sharing mode will be lost)</li>
    <li>Constant Throughput Timer (Calculate throughput based on will be lost)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
The numbers that appear to the left of the green box are the number of active threads / total number of threads, 
these only apply to a locally run test; they do not include any threads started on remote systems when using client-server mode, (see <bugzilla>54152</bugzilla>).
</p>

<p>
Note that there is a bug in Java on some Linux systems that manifests
itself as the following error when running the test cases or JMeter itself:
<pre>
 [java] WARNING: Couldn't flush user prefs:
 java.util.prefs.BackingStoreException:
 java.lang.IllegalArgumentException: Not supported: indent-number
</pre>
This does not affect JMeter operation.
</p>

<!-- =================== Incompatible changes =================== -->

<h2>Incompatible changes</h2>

<p>Webservice sampler now adds to request the headers that are set through Header Manager, these were previously ignored</p>

<p>jdbcsampler.cachesize property has been removed, it previously limited the size of a per connection cache of Map &lt; String, PreparedStatement &gt; , it also limited the size of this
map which held the PreparedStatement for SQL queries. This limitation provoked a bug <bugzilla>53995</bugzilla>. 
It has been removed so now size of these 2 maps is not limited anymore. This change changes behaviour as starting from this version no PreparedStatement will be closed during the test.</p>

<p>Starting with this version JSR223 Test Elements that have an invalid filename (not existing or unreadable) will make test fail instead of making the element silently work</p>
<!-- =================== Bug fixes =================== -->

<h2>Bug fixes</h2>

<h3>HTTP Samplers and Proxy</h3>
<ul>
<li>Don't log spurious warning messages when using concurrent pool embedded downloads with Cache Manager or CookieManager</li>
<li><bugzilla>54057</bugzilla>- Proxy option to set user and password at startup (-u and -a) not working with HTTPClient 4</li>
</ul>

<h3>Other Samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>53997</bugzilla> - LDAP Extended Request: Escape ampersand (&amp;), left angle bracket (&lt;) 
and right angle bracket (&gt;) in search filter tag in XML response data</li>
<li><bugzilla>53995</bugzilla> - AbstractJDBCTestElement shares PreparedStatement between multi-threads</li>
<li><bugzilla>54119</bugzilla> - HTTP 307 response is not redirected</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54088</bugzilla> - The type video/f4m is text, not binary</li>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54058</bugzilla> - In HTTP Request Defaults, the value of field "Embedded URLs must match: is not saved if the check box "Retrieve All  Embedded Resources" is not checked.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>53975</bugzilla> - Variables replacement doesn't work with option "Delay thread creation until needed"</li>
<li><bugzilla>54055</bugzilla> - View Results tree: = signs are stripped from parameter values at HTTP tab</li>
<li><bugzilla>54129</bugzilla> - Search Feature does not find text although existing in elements </li>
</ul>

<!-- =================== Improvements =================== -->

<h2>Improvements</h2>

<h3>HTTP Samplers</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Other samplers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54004</bugzilla> - Webservice Sampler : Allow adding headers to request with Header Manager</li>
<li><bugzilla>54106</bugzilla> - JSR223TestElement should check for file existence when a filename is set instead of using Text Area content </li>
<li><bugzilla>54107</bugzilla> - JSR223TestElement : Enable compilation and caching of Script Text</li>
</ul>

<h3>Controllers</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54131</bugzilla> - ForEach Controller : Add start and end index for looping over variables</li>
<li><bugzilla>54132</bugzilla> - Module Controller GUI : Improve rendering of referenced controller</li>
</ul>

<h3>Listeners</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Timers, Assertions, Config, Pre- &amp; Post-Processors</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>I18N</h3>
<ul>
</ul>

<h3>General</h3>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>54005</bugzilla> - HTTP Mirror Server : Add special headers "X-" to control Response status and response content</li>
<li><bugzilla>53875</bugzilla> - Include suggested defaults for URL filters on HTTP Proxy</li>
<li><bugzilla>54031</bugzilla> - Add tooltip to running/total threads indicator </li>
<li>Webservice (SOAP) Request has been deprecated</li>
</ul>

<h2>Non-functional changes</h2>
<ul>
<li><bugzilla>53956</bugzilla> - Add ability to paste (a list of values) from clipboard for Header Manager</li>
<li>Updated to HttpComponents Client 4.2.2 (from 4.2.1)</li>
<li><bugzilla>54110</bugzilla> - BSFTestElement and JSR223TestElement should use shared super-class for common fields</li>
</ul>

</section> 
</body> 
</document>