<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
	 <author email="bburns@apache.org">Brendan Burns, et al.</author>
	 <title>Apache JMeter</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
	<section name="Apache JMeter">
	<p>
	  <b>Apache JMeter</b> is a 100% pure Java desktop application designed 
	  to load test functional behavior and measure performance.  It was 
	  originally designed for testing Web Applications but has
	  since expanded to other test functions.
	</p>
	<h2>What can I do with it?</h2>
	<p>
	  Apache JMeter may be used to test performance both on static and dynamic
	  resources (files, Servlets, Perl scripts, Java Objects, Data Bases and 
	  Queries, FTP Servers and more). It can be used to simulate a heavy
load on a server, network or object to test its strength or to analyze 
overall performance under different load types. You can use it to make a 
graphical analysis of performance or to test your server/script/object 
behavior under heavy concurrent load.
</p>
<p><a HREF="user_manual/index.html">Using JMeter</a></p>
<h2>What does it do?</h2>
<p>Apache JMeter features include:</p>
<ul>
	<li>Can load and performance test HTTP and FTP servers as well as
		arbitrary database queries (via JDBC)</li>
	<li>Complete portability and <b>100% Java purity</b>.</li>
	<li>Full <b>Swing</b> and lightweight component support (precompiled JAR uses packages 
		<code>javax.swing.*</code>).</li>
	<li>Full <b>multithreading</b> framework allows concurrent sampling by many threads and
		simultaneous sampling of different functions by seperate thread groups.</li>
	<li>Careful <b>GUI</b> design allows faster operation and more precise timings.</li>
	<li>Caching and offline analysis/replaying of test results.</li>
	<li> Highly Extensible:
	  <ul>
		<li>Pluggable Samplers allow unlimited testing capabilities.</li>
		<li>Several load statistics may be choosen with <b>pluggable timers</b>.</li>
		<li>Data analysis and <b>visualization plugins</b> allow great extendibility 
		as well as personalization.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>
</ul>
</section>
</body>
</document>
