<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
	 <author email="bburns@apache.org">Brendan Burns, et al.</author>
	 <title>Running Apache JMeter</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="Running Apache JMeter">

  <p>Apache JMeter comes with startup scripts to help you run the application. They are
  located in the directory /bin and are called jmeter for UNIX systems and jmeter.bat for
  Windows systems. Make sure the file <code>ApacheJMeter.jar</code> and <code>jmeter.properties</code> is located in the same
  directory and type <tt>jmeter</tt> to start.</p>

  <p>These scripts assume you already have a JRE installed, and that the command &quot;java&quot; is in your path.</p>

  <p>In addition to the standard Java libraries that come with the JRE, you may need to download two other API's:</p>
  <ul>
	<li><STRONG>Mail</STRONG>: <a HREF="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/index.html">Java Mail<sup><font
size="-2">tm</font></sup></a> API as well as the <a
href="http://www.javasoft.com/beans/glasgow/jaf">javax.activation</a> API 	from <a
HREF="http://java.sun.com">Sun</a>.<br/> 	To enable the MailVisualizer, add mail.jar and activation.jar from Sun's
JavaMail download to your classpath or $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/ext directory, or you can drop the jar files into the /lib directory where JMeter is installed.</li>
<li><p><strong>JSSE</strong>: <a
href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/">JSSE</a> is available from <a HREF="http://java.sun.com">sun</a>.<br/> 	JSSE
is an SSL encryption provider that is used to enable JMeter to test websites using the https protocol.</p> 	<p>To turn
SSL support on, make sure all the jars that come with JSSE are in your classpath (jsse.jar, jnet.jar, jcert.jar), and
modify <strong>jmeter.properties</strong> to instruct JMeter which SSL Provider you are using.  For JSSE, set the line
as 	follows:</p> 	<p>ssl.provider=com.sun.net.ssl.internal.ssl.Provider</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section name="Modifying Properties">

  <p>If you wish to modify the properties with which JMeter runs you need to
  either modify the jmeter.properties inside of the /bin directory or create
  your own copy of the jmeter.properties and specify it in the command line
  (jmeter [properties file]).
  </p>
  <b>Properties to modify</b>
  <ul>
  <li><b>search_paths:</b> If you have developed new extensions to JMeter, you can tell JMeter where to find your classes by adding the name of the
  jar, or the directory where your classes live.</li>
  <li><b>user.dir:</b> The directory JMeter will first go to for saving and loading test scripts.</li>
  <li><b>remote_hosts:</b> Comma-delimited list of remote JMeter hosts.  If you are running JMeter in a distributed environment, list the machines where
  you have JMeter remote servers running.  This will allow you to control those servers from this machine's GUI</li>
  <li><b>not_in_menu:</b> A list of components you do not want to see in JMeter's menus.  As JMeter has more and more components added, you may wish to
  customize your JMeter to show only those components you are interested in.  You may list their classname or their class label (the string that appears
  in JMeter's UI) here, and they will no longer appear in the menu's.</li>
  </ul>

<p align="center"><font size="-1">Copyright (c) 1998-99 <a href="http://java.apache.org">The Java Apache
Project</a>.<br/>
$Id$</font> <br/>
<font size="-1">All rights reserved.</font></p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
